<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Vox belli, or, An alarum to vvarre</title>
            <title>Vox belli.</title>
            <author>Barnes, Thomas, Minister of St. Margaret's, New Fish Street, London.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1626</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 111 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04657</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1478</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118246</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853454</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853454</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18837</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04657)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18837)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 872:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Vox belli, or, An alarum to vvarre</title>
                  <title>Vox belli.</title>
                  <author>Barnes, Thomas, Minister of St. Margaret's, New Fish Street, London.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 41, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. L[ownes] for Nathanael Newbery,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1626.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18837:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18837:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>VOXBELLI, OR, AN ALARVM TO VVARRE.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>H.L.</hi> for <hi>Nathanael Newbery.</hi> 1626.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18837:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18837:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, Sir <hi>Horatio Veere,</hi> Knight, Baron of Tilbury, &amp;c. all bleſſings wiſhed, that concerne this life, and that which is to come.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am not ignorant, that great is the miſchiefe and miſery of warre; <hi>than which</hi> (as<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Maxim. Tyrius. <hi>Diſſert.</hi> 14. <hi>p.</hi> 143.</note> one ſaith) <hi>no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing amongſt humane occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences is more ſorrowfull, leſſe pleaſant:</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Theat. Mund p. 85.</note> Beaſts, in their kinde, having more reſt, &amp; pleaſure than they whoſe life is led in warfare. For whereas the beaſt <hi>ſleeps</hi> the night in its cave &amp; den, the <hi>Souldier</hi> takes his reſt at the ſigne of the Moone,<note n="c" place="margin">2. Cor. 11.27.</note> 
               <hi>in watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings often, in faſtings often;</hi> ſubject to the violence of all Martiall ſtormes, uncertain what the event and ſucceſſe will be: whoſe office is, upon the Trumpets ſound, eyther <hi>mortem ferre,</hi> or <hi>inferre,</hi> to ſlay or bee ſlaine; and neyther of both, without ſome prejudice. If he <hi>fals,</hi> his wife, his children, his kindred, his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey have the loſſe of him: if he <hi>conquers,</hi> his <hi>riſing</hi> is the <hi>ruine</hi> of others; his <hi>riches</hi> the <hi>ſpoyle</hi> of others, his <hi>joy</hi> the <hi>mourning</hi> of others: inſomuch, that hee may cry out as <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> did (when after ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny victories, hee received his Triumph in <hi>Rome): When I ſaw the poore captives in iron chaines, deſolate Widowes bereaved of their husbands, diſconſolate Orphans deprived of their parents, a
<pb facs="tcp:18837:3"/> great deale of treaſure gotten by force, &amp; thought upon the number of thoſe that were dead; albeit I outwardly triumphed, yet inwardly lamented, and wept teares of bloud.</hi> In times of war, Countryes are waſted, Cities diſpoyled, Temples profaned, Religion deſpiſed, equity ſuppreſſed, humanity defaced; &amp; what cruelty, what impiety not notoriouſly practiſed? All <hi>this</hi> conſidered, <hi>I</hi> may (poſsibly) be cenſured by criticall carpers, for ſetting pen to paper on ſuch a ſubject, and eſpecially for <hi>inciting</hi> to ſo bloudy a buſineſſe. But (the call being not <hi>mine</hi> but the <hi>Lords</hi>) I ſhall the more willingly beare the burthen of any undeſerved blame, if what I have written may prevaile to provoke <hi>them</hi> whom it concernes, to a readineſſe to ſuccour the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed <hi>Church</hi> in forreine parts. If it be demanded what hath emboldened me to crave <hi>your Honours</hi> patronage for theſe few papers; I can anſwer, nothing, but partly your <hi>love</hi> to <hi>Chriſt</hi> his <hi>cauſe,</hi> as you are a <hi>Beleever;</hi> and partly your <hi>place</hi> in <hi>Gods field,</hi> as a warlike Commander. If the <hi>Author</hi> be thought pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous, notwithſtanding <hi>theſe</hi> motives, cenſure his boldneſſe at your pleaſure; but I beſeech you be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſhelter the <hi>Matter (not needleſſe for theſe times)</hi> from the worlds diſpleaſure: ſo ſhall you engage <hi>him</hi> to be a ſuitor to the Throne of <hi>Grace,</hi> for your <hi>Honours</hi> proſperity in warre and peace, who is</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Your Hon:</salute>
               <signed>ready to be commanded in the Lord, THO: BARNES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18837:3"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>OX BELLI.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a ſaying of one of the <hi>Fathers,</hi> in a written diſcourſe to one of his friends;<note n="a" place="margin">Facito ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid operis, ut te ſemper dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolus inveniat occupatum. <hi>Hieron ad Ruſt. Monach.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Be alwaies doing ſomething, that Satan may never finde thee do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing.</hi> The <hi>ſlothfull</hi> perſon doth the wiſeman ſend to the ſilly <hi>Piſmyre,</hi> to learne her wayes<note n="b" place="margin">Prov. 6.6.</note>. The Apoſtle charged the <hi>Theſſalonian</hi> Church, that <hi>hee that would not labour ſhould not eate</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">2. Theſ. 3.10.</note>. And our Saviour himſelfe pronounceth that ſervant <hi>bleſſed,</hi> whom when his Maſter commeth, he ſhall find <hi>doing</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Luke 12.43.</note>. All this, to give us to underſtand, that<note n="e" place="margin">Nider For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nic. l. 1. c. 1. p. 9.</note> 
               <hi>idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> is permitted to <hi>none: emploiment</hi> (the<note n="f" place="margin">Hieron. ad Ruſt. Monach.</note> Devills diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieter) is required of<note n="*" place="margin">Nid. ſupr.</note> all. For the ſluggard takes no care but to<note n="g" place="margin">Leo Ser. 5. in Epiph.</note> pamper his belly; makes his life odious,<note n="h" place="margin">Sen. Epi. 19.</note> and beaſtly,<note n="i" place="margin">Bernard.</note> diſableth nature to doe <hi>its</hi> duetie<note n="k" place="margin">Caſſian. l. 10.</note>, defi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth his ſoule with a world of iniquities<note n="l" place="margin">Senec. Epiſt. 19.</note>, diſeaſeth his body with abundance of maladies, and expoſeth<note n="m" place="margin">Proſp Aqui. de vit. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templ.</note> both to eternall miſery, in an utter excluſion from Gods bleſſed preſence in his Kingdome of glory. Now, becauſe not to bee <hi>well exerciſed is to bee ill exerciſed</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Chryſoſt. de virt. &amp; vitio.</note>, and the doing of that which is <hi>naught,</hi> is as bad, if not worſe, <hi>as</hi> the doing of <hi>nothing:</hi> Therefore the maine
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18837:4"/> object of our exerciſe, muſt be <hi>Gods</hi> buſineſſe. Now, in as much as the Lord hath many and differing workes for man to doe; workes of <hi>peace, (he being the God of Peace</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">2. Theſ. 3.16.</note>:) workes of bloud, (he being <hi>a man of Warre</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Iſa 42.13.</note>) <hi>neither</hi> of <hi>theſe</hi> muſt bee omitted, when need requireth, and occaſion ſerves for the doing of them. Which thing the Prophet <hi>Ieremy</hi> taking into due conſideration, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alſo a Propheticall Diviner of <hi>Moabs</hi> deſtruction,) could not but earneſtly incite to this work of the Lord, of <hi>not withholding</hi> the ſword from bloud. Hee was not ignorant that <hi>peace</hi> is a<note n="q" place="margin">Dion. Chryſ. orat. 40. p. 244.</note> 
               <hi>better,</hi> yea a <hi>bleſſeder</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Syneſ. orat. de regn. p 14.</note> thing than <hi>war;</hi> and that<note n="ſ" place="margin">Baſil. Seleuc. orat. 23. p. 207.</note> 
               <hi>for one armie of men to come bandied like e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies against another, is</hi> (as an Ancient once ſpake) <hi>both grievous and cruell:</hi> In which reſpect, <hi>Bleſſed are the Peace-makers,</hi> (our <hi>Saviours</hi> text<note n="t" place="margin">Matth. 5.9.</note>,) would (to our ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) a great deale more fitly have dropped from his pen. But it ſeemes, he knew withall, that a <hi>lawfull warre</hi> is to bee preferred before an <hi>unlawfull peace;</hi> and that warre with <hi>Moab,</hi> would be as well <hi>Iſraels</hi> peace, as the <hi>Chaldees</hi> victory: (<note n="v" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ariſt. de Repub. l. 8. c. 15. <hi>Propter pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem bellum pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratur.</hi> Syneſ. orat. de Reg. p. 14.</note> peace and<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Est enim belli finis victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria.</hi> Plutarch. Scipio. in vitis to 3. lat. edit. in 4. p. 465.</note> victory being the ends of warre.) For which reaſon, this good man, Gods Pen-man, muſt be borne with, though he writes a Text in red letters, having the <hi>ſword</hi> for his pen, <hi>bloud</hi> for his inke, the <hi>curſe</hi> for his ſtile.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <note place="margin">Ier. 48.10.</note>Curſed be he that keepeth backe his ſword from bloud.</head>
               <p>A Text ſo terrible, that at the firſt it made me fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to meddle with it; eſpecially, when I contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plated with my ſelfe, that it would compell me to ſpeak of <hi>curſes</hi> and <hi>woes</hi> in a land of <hi>grace:</hi> of <hi>bloud</hi> and <hi>blowes</hi> in a land of <hi>peace.</hi> But when I conſidered that there are <hi>Canaanites</hi> to be ſmitten at home, Chriſtians to bee ſuccoured abroad, I tooke heart to venture this field; perſwading my ſelfe, it would not prove unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: albeit, I am cauſed to doubt of the accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe of it, by the conſciouſneſſe of my weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18837:4"/> to weild my weapon as I ſhould.</p>
               <p>The words (being a commination or threatning) doe cut themſelves into two peeces; a <hi>Quid,</hi> and a <hi>Quis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The parts.</note> a <hi>Subject,</hi> and an <hi>Object.</hi> A <hi>thing</hi> threatned, a <hi>party</hi> threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Subject</hi> or <hi>thing</hi> threatned, is malediction, <hi>[Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.]</hi> The <hi>Object</hi> or <hi>man</hi> threatned, is <hi>[hee that keepeth backe his ſword from bloud.]</hi> From the firſt (which muſt firſt be handled) we may collect this point,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Doct.</hi> 1. Gods Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets were wont to threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</note> That <hi>it was the practiſe of Gods Prophets in former ages, to denounce the Curſe in their Sermons at ſometimes.</hi> They did not alwayes come with <hi>peace, peace,</hi> and words of bleſſing in their mouthes. Their ſongs (like<note n="z" place="margin">Pſal. 101.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Davids</hi>) had a due mixture, and were compoſed of <hi>judgement,</hi> as well as <hi>mercie.</hi> The word <hi>Curſed</hi> (as here you ſee, and elſe-where may ſee) flowes from the <hi>mouth,</hi> falls from the pen of old <hi>Ieremy,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Ier. 11.3. &amp; 17.5.</note> for all he was ſo tender boweld, ſo mercifull hearted a man. The writings of <hi>Moſes</hi> are full of <hi>Curſes.</hi> Twenty times at leaſt in the booke of <hi>Deuteronomie,</hi> hath hee this phraſe up, <hi>Curſed be he</hi> that doth <hi>this,</hi> and <hi>Curſed bee be</hi> that doth <hi>that.</hi> Reade a whole catalogue in the 27. <hi>chapter,</hi> from the 15. verſe to the end; in the 28. <hi>chapter,</hi> from the 16 verſe to the 21. The Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> is in the ſame ſtraine. <hi>The</hi> CURSE <hi>hath devoured the earth</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Iſa. 24.6.</note>. <hi>The ſinner being an hundred yeeres old, ſhall be</hi> ACCURSED<note n="b" place="margin">&amp; 65.20.</note>. So is <hi>Malachy, Curſed</hi> bee the deceiver<note n="c" place="margin">Mal. 1.14.</note>. I will ſend a CURSE upon you, and will CURSE your bleſſings: yea, I have CURSED them already<note n="d" place="margin">&amp; 2.2.</note>. Yee are CUR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SED with a CURSE<note n="e" place="margin">&amp; 3.9.</note>. And ſo were the reſt of the holy Prophets. Never a one amongſt them all, did alwayes abſtaine from thundering, from threatning, as is very manifeſt in their writings. Neither need wee marvaile any whit at it: For they had both <hi>cauſe</hi> to doe it, and a <hi>call</hi> unto it.</p>
               <p>Firſt, they had <hi>cauſe</hi> to threaten. In <hi>their</hi> times the <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> Law of the Lord was tranſgreſſed; vice abounded, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue decayed: commanded dueties were either wholly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18837:5"/> omitted, or but coldly performed; forbidden courſes were eagerly followed, delightfully walked in. Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> meane elſe the many and manifold complaints of the Lord againſt <hi>Iſrael</hi> for her ſins, againſt <hi>Iacob</hi> for her tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions? Now the righteous God hath ſo ordered, that where the <hi>breach</hi> of the Law goes before, the <hi>curſe</hi> of the Law muſt follow after<note n="f" place="margin">Deut. 28.15.16. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Theod. quaeſt. 34. in Deut. p. 170.</note>. Which wiſe and juſt or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of the Lord, his holy Prophets having weighed, could not, did not, ſpare to ſpend the arrowes of the Lawes <hi>rigorous curſes,</hi> when they ſaw <hi>moſt</hi> to have <hi>ſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> prone to ſwerve from the Lawes <hi>righteous courſes.</hi> Had not <hi>David</hi> (who was a <hi>Prophet</hi> as well as a King) juſt cauſe to declaime woes, when the men of his time did rebelliouſly decline Gods waies? <hi>Curſed be the proud which doe erre,</hi> or becauſe they erre, <hi>from thy</hi> Commandements<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 119.21.</note>.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> Secondly, they had a <hi>call</hi> to this ſervice. The ſame God that gave them a <hi>charge,</hi> and <hi>charter,</hi> to <hi>comfort</hi> ſome,<note n="h" place="margin">Iſa. 40.1.</note> ſealed them a <hi>commiſſion</hi> to curſe others; as knowing<note n="i" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Theod. quaeſt. 36. in Deut. p. 172.</note> 
                  <hi>wicked men to be ſooner moved, better wrought upon by menaces, than promiſes. Ieremie's</hi> commiſſion wee may reade at large in the beginning of his <hi>Propheſie. See, I have ſet thee this day over the Nations, and over the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, to roote out, to pull downe, to deſtroy. I will utter my judgements against them, touching all their wickedneſſe: Thou therefore gird up thy loynes, ariſe, and ſpeake unto them all that I command thee</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">Ier. 1.10.16.17.</note>. <hi>Goe and cry in the eares of Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">Ier. 2.2.</note>. <hi>Ezekiels</hi> call and commiſſion to this, we have in the ſecond and third chapters of his Propheſie, where wee may read that the Lord himſelfe ſet him upon his feet<note n="m" place="margin">Exek. 2.1.</note>, put courage into his heart<note n="n" place="margin">Ibid. ver. 6.</note>, words into his mouth<note n="o" place="margin">cha. 9.1.2.3.</note>,<note n="p" place="margin">cha. 2.9.10.</note> ſpread before him, opened vnto him the Legall Roll writ on both ſides with lamentation, mourning, and woe, which he was to<note n="q" place="margin">Ezek. 3.4.</note> preach, and reade in the deafe eares of rebellious <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Vpon the like warrant did the other <hi>Prophets</hi> doe the like worke. It was their <hi>priviledge</hi> to denounce the Curſe, therefore it was their <hi>practiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:18837:5"/>
               <p>Which being ſo, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
                  </label> who ſees not how worthy of blame all thoſe bee who take on, and cry out againſt <hi>us,</hi> that are Gods Meſſengers, for ſpeaking to them at ſome times in the terrible <hi>language</hi> of the <hi>Law.</hi> Speake wee <hi>comfortably</hi> to <hi>all</hi> at <hi>all times,</hi> they can well beare it. Preach we <hi>curſes</hi> againſt <hi>any</hi> at <hi>any time,</hi> they cannot endure it: <hi>So</hi>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">Sim. Caſſian. de relig. Chriſt. l. 6 c. 1. fol. 132. col. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>grievous to mans eare is Gods Word, when it convinceth him of ſinne, or goes about</hi> (with an holy violence) <hi>to plucke him from the world, and ſave him from hell;</hi> as the threatnings of it are for all theſe purpoſes. Why may not <hi>wee</hi> doe as our Predeceſſors the <hi>Prophets</hi> did? Is our Charter <hi>leſſe?</hi> nay, is not <hi>our</hi> Commiſſion larger than theirs was? <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> who was <hi>greater than the rest of the</hi>
                  <note n="ſ" place="margin">Mat. 11.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Prophets</hi> (as well in reſpect of<note n="t" place="margin">Bucer. in Mat. 11.</note> his office of preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Chriſt</hi> after he was borne, as of his act<note n="v" place="margin">Euthym. ca. 19. in Mat. 11.</note> of acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging Chriſt, by <hi>ſpringing in the wombe</hi> before hee was borne) was <hi>leſſe than the leaſt in the kingdome of Heaven;</hi> that is, not onely leſſe than the bleſſed ſoules of glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Saints, in actuall happineſſe<note n="x" place="margin">Lyr. in Mat. 11.</note>, or leſſe in nature than<note n="y" place="margin">Stella in Luc. to. 1. fol. 179 col. 2.</note> the Celeſtiall Angells, which ever ſtand in Gods glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious preſence; but alſo leſſe than the leaſt of <hi>Chriſts</hi> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Apoſtles: leſſe than the<note n="z" place="margin">Calv. in Mat. 11.</note> Miniſters of the Goſpell, who are the laſt in time of the <hi>Ministeriall</hi> function, of the leaſt eſteeme in the worlds opinion. Now, that <hi>Iohn</hi> thundred, may not <hi>wee</hi> then threat? Did God bid <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie</hi> utter his <hi>judgements, Moſes</hi> curſe, and <hi>Malachie</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne; and doth hee forbid us to doe the like? I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe we are Miniſters of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> Interpreters of the <hi>new</hi> Covenant, and in <hi>that reſpect, doe differ from the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, the</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <hi>Legis Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretes, &amp; cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des Prophetae erant.</hi> Scult. in Iſa. ca. 1 pag. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Keepers, the Interpreters of the old.</hi> Muſt we for <hi>that cauſe</hi> never preach nor preſſe the <hi>Law?</hi> Ah frivolous and groundleſſe concluſion. The <hi>Goſpell</hi> it ſelfe is a <hi>law;</hi> the law of <hi>Grace,</hi> the law of <hi>Faith</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">1. Cor. 9.21.</note>. It hath a<note n="c" place="margin">Chryſoſt. Hom. 15. in Mat. Euthym. in Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. c 5. fol. 26. C.F.</note> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding, a forbidding authority, as well as the Law. Doth the Law forbid the <hi>practiſe</hi> of ſinne, the Goſpell forbids the principle of ſinne<note n="d" place="margin">Nazianz. orat. 42. p. 691. Baſil. edit. lat.</note>. The one forbids the end, the other the beginning: The one doth not more po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werfully
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18837:6"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:18837:6"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:18837:7"/> ſtrike at the<note n="e" place="margin">Iſid. Pelu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. l. 1. epiſt. 458.</note> branches &amp; fruit, <hi>actuall tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> than the other doth at the roote, <hi>originall corruption.</hi> Not that the <hi>Law</hi> meddles not with <hi>concupiſcence</hi> at all; but is not<note n="f" place="margin">Lombard l 3. epiſt 40. A. fol. 300.</note> ſo univerſally, ſo <hi>eminently,</hi> ſo<note n="g" place="margin">Hag. Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. Evang. ca. 15. ſect. 13. pa. 51.</note> 
                  <hi>evidently</hi> againſt it as the <hi>Goſpell</hi> is. Yea, this<note n="h" place="margin">Theophil. Praefat. in Mat.</note> 
                  <hi>Goſpell doth threaten pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment,</hi> as well as the Law: <hi>Hee that beleeveth not, is condemned already</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Iohn 3.18.</note>. <hi>If any man love not the Lord Ieſus, let him be accurſed</hi>
                  <note n="k" place="margin">1. Cor. 16.22.</note>. <hi>The Lord Ieſus ſhall be revealed from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to render vengeance on all thoſe that know not God, and that obey not the Goſpell</hi>
                  <note n="l" place="margin">2. Theſ. 1.8.</note>. Are not theſe ſentences in the <hi>New</hi> Teſtament? Now, hath the Goſpell it ſelfe, it's ſowre, as well as it's ſweete; it's bottles of venegar, as well as it's barrells of wine; And muſt we Miniſters <hi>of the Goſpell,</hi> in every paſſage of every Sermon, deliver forth ſweet wine? never any tart vinegar, be it never ſo needfull, never ſo uſefull? Our bleſſed Saviour, the ſweeteſt Angell of peace that ever came into the world; holy <hi>Paul,</hi> the moſt Evangelicall Preacher ſince Chriſt, that ever the Church had, and the reſt of the holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, were not ſo ſtinted, ſo ſtreightned; but they had their <hi>Vae's,</hi> their <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">The very word of the Septuagint in our Text which is tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated <hi>curſed.</hi>
                  </note>, their woes and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledictions, in their Sermons and ſayings<note n="n" place="margin">Conferre with theſe Scriptures. Mat. 11.21.22. c. 18.7. c. 23.13 <hi>&amp; ſaepius eodem capite.</hi> Luc. 6.2.25.26. c. 11.42.43.44. &amp;c. Ioh 7.49. Gal 3.10 ver. 13. Iude ver. 11. Apoc. 8.13. c. 9. ver. 12. c. 11.1. c. 12.12.</note>: Why then ſhould <hi>wee,</hi> the <hi>Apoſtles ſucceſſors,</hi> have a tye from <hi>threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> put upon our tongues?</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Object. Anſw.</note>But will you compare with the bleſſed Apoſtles? I anſwer, we doe not, we dare not. Perſonall compariſons wee may not make betwixt them and us; yet every branch and limme of our Miniſteriall function we muſt maintaine. As we are inferiour to the Apoſtles, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of infallibility of judgement about fundamentall truthes, and eminency in other gifts and graces; ſo wee differ from them in other things: Firſt, our calling is not ſo immediate as <hi>theirs</hi> was; <hi>Meanes</hi> of <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Tongues,</hi> provided for the purpoſe, muſt fit us for the worke of the Miniſtry. Fiſhermen, and Toll-gatherers, may not <hi>now</hi> runne immediately, as <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Matthew</hi> might, and did, from their boates and nets, and ſeates of cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18837:7"/> (as the manner of ſome illiterate, meerely un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quallified Artificers is,) to become Doctors of the Law. Secondly, wee have not ſuch revelations as they had; nor thirdly, the gift of Propheſie; nor fourthly, of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous faith: <hi>All which the Apoſtles had in common with the Prophets</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Sculter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n Iſa. c 1. conc. 1 p. 7. 8.</note>: yet notwithſtanding theſe differences, Chriſts beloved Diſciple, S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> heard <hi>a great voice out of the Temple, ſaying to the SEAVEN ANGELS, Goe your way, powre out the Vialls of the wrath of God up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Revel 16.1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note>. that is, he foreſaw the Miniſters of the Goſpell in<note n="q" place="margin">Parae. in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poc col. 805. Richard de S Vict. p 2. l. 5. ſup. Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal. c. 2. fol. 99. C.</note> 
                  <hi>theſe times,</hi> to have commiſſion given them from the God of heaven, to powre forth Gods curſes (comminatorily in their Sermons) upon the heads of<note n="r" place="margin">Ibid.</note> earthly minded men. And indeed,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Tunc enim producit Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſus lignum ſcientiae boni &amp; mali, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do Praedicator regnum Dei proponit bonis, &amp; quando ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis ſupplicium inferni exponi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>Rampeog. figur. Biblic. p. 272.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>then Paradiſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces the Tree of knowledge, of good and evill, when the Preacher promiſeth mercies to the good, threatneth judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the bad.</hi> Had wee no <hi>cauſe</hi> to curſe, it were another matter: but in theſe times iniquity doth ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound, and<note n="t" place="margin">Plerique hâc tempeſtate mortales ita peccatorum ſordibus volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantur. <hi>Hier. Ferrarienſ. Triumph cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis proem. p. 1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>mortall men doe ſo wallow in ſinnes ſordid filth,</hi> that wee muſt of neceſſity at ſometimes bee the ſonnes of thunder. Let none therefore bee ſo mercileſſe to <hi>themſelves,</hi> ſo injurious to <hi>us,</hi> as to finde fault when we threaten: <hi>Mercileſſe</hi> they are to <hi>themſelves,</hi> in that they would have us to let them have liberty to ſinne to death without controll, having no ſtomacke (as indeed they ſhould have<note n="v" place="margin">Rampeog. figur. Biblic. p. 272.</note>) to eate of that Paradiſe fruit, of the knowledge of the evill of puniſhment, which may make them abhorre the evill of ſinne. And <hi>injurious</hi> they are to <hi>us,</hi> in that they would have us bring the guilt of their bloud upon our owne <hi>heads,</hi> while (like <hi>Locuſts</hi> (one of the plagues of Egypt<note n="x" place="margin">Exod. 10.</note>) <hi>which loves the ſpring time, and fat paſtures</hi>) hopping to their houſes, feeding at their Tables, and fawning upon them for their favour &amp; gifts, we ſhould ſooth them in their ſinnes, and ſo ſpoile their ſoules. I would not willingly have paſſed this point, without a word of adviſe to my brethren in the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, that they would not ſpare to direct legall curſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18837:8"/> godleſſe men for their lawleſſe courſes: but that I would without longer ſtay leade you on to the ſecond part of the Text, the <hi>party threatned,</hi> or the <hi>object</hi> of the threatning. <hi>[He that keepeth backe</hi> (or withholdeth) <hi>his ſword from bloud.]</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Part.</hi> 2.</note>I will not here be <hi>curious</hi> in a <hi>ſubdiviſion,</hi> leſt I prove <hi>ridiculous</hi> in obſervation, and by a Fryer-like ſtragling into quaint deſcants, more pleaſing to the fleſh, than wholeſome for the ſoule, I bring my ſelfe within the compaſſe of the guilt of taking Gods Name in vaine. Let us hold our ſelves to the approvedeſt, profitableſt method of handling Scripture Texts; firſt, <hi>commenting,</hi> and ſearching out the <hi>meaning:</hi> next, <hi>concluding,</hi> and fetching out the matter.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> The Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretation.</note>The firſt may wee diſpatch in a word or two, the words are ſo plaine. <hi>Curſed be [HE]</hi> what <hi>he?</hi> eyther the whole body of the <hi>Chaldaean</hi> or Babylonian <hi>Armie,</hi> or any particular member, eſpecially the King and head of that body. <hi>[That withholdeth his ſword.]</hi> Marke, hee doth not ſay, <hi>that puts not out,</hi> as implying without a call: but, that keepeth back, or (as <hi>Arias Montanus</hi>) that<note n="z" place="margin">Qui prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet.</note> forbiddeth, or (as the <hi>Septuagint</hi>) that<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> exempteth, as though he would plead a priviledge for his ſword, to keepe ſcabbard, when hee is commanded to plucke it forth. <hi>[From bloud]</hi> Whoſe bloud? the bloud of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abites, a proud, diſobedient, envious, malicious people, noted enemies to Gods Church, and branded for guilty of many hainous crimes; ſome of which I ſhall touch upon anon. You have the <hi>meaning.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>matter</hi> next (whoſe courſe comes now) multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies upon us into many points;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> The mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which conſiſts in Doctrinall points.</note> ſome <hi>indirect,</hi> ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect: all which to handle, twice as much time as I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for this ſubject would not ſuffice us. Wee will name no more than we intend to handle, we will handle no more, than wee may well diſpatch within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of a reaſonable time; and they ſhall bee theſe three.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:18837:8"/>
               <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Doct. <hi>2.</hi> or <hi>1.</hi> from the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part.</note> that <hi>God ſometimes ſmiteth one wicked man by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nd of another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>that the ſword may not bee ſtretched out to bloud without a call.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, that to bid the ſword keepe ſcabbard, when God calls it forth, expoſeth to the Curſe.</p>
               <p>Of theſe in their order. And firſt of the firſt.<note n="b" place="margin">Solet Deus malos per ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los punire. <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae. in Gen. col. 1074.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>God ſometimes drawes the ſword of one wicked man against an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</hi> Here the Chaldaeans, an impious, idolatrous peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, are ſummoned to battell againſt the Moabites; and <hi>Ieremie,</hi> Gods Prophet, brings <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Gods people, the certaine newes and tidings of it. In the<note n="*" place="margin">Hoc primum bellum legitur in hiſtorijs mundi, nec pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fanae habent tam antiquum, ne dum anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quius ullum. <hi>Ib. col. 1069.</hi>
                  </note> firſt field that was ever fought, which did happen, as ſome reckon, in the<note n="c" place="margin">Ergo <hi>84.</hi> anno circiter aetatis Abrami haec geſta videntur: mundi anno <hi>2092. Ibid. col. 1071.</hi>
                  </note> foureſcore and fourth yeere of <hi>Abrahams</hi> age, the 2092. of the world, we have ten <hi>wicked</hi> Kings hard at it, five againſt five in the Vale of Siddim<note n="d" place="margin">Gen 14. the firſt 13. verſes.</note>. In the booke of Iudges, we ſhall finde the unrighteous Midia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites ſheathing their ſwords in <hi>their owne bowels,</hi> and every man drawing upon his neighbour<note n="e" place="margin">Iudg. 7.20.22.</note>. When the Tribes of Iſrael grew corrupted, the Lord threatned by his ſervant <hi>Eſay,</hi> that <hi>every one ſhould eate the fleſh of his owne arme, Manaſſeh Ephraim, and Ephraim Manaſſeh, and</hi> that <hi>they</hi> both <hi>ſhould be againſt Iudah</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Iſa. 9.21.</note>. The ſame Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet foretold the deſtruction of <hi>Babylon</hi> by the <hi>Medes</hi> and Perſians<note n="g" place="margin">Iſa. 13.27.</note>; the overthrow of the <hi>Egyptians</hi> by the hands of the Aſſyrians<note n="h" place="margin">Iſa. 19.2.</note>. <hi>Saul,</hi> a graceleſſe reprobate man, put <hi>Amalek</hi> (a<note n="i" place="margin">Deut. 25.19.</note> curſed people) to the edge of the ſword<note n="k" place="margin">1. Sam. 15.7.</note>. <hi>Iehu</hi> an Idoll-ſerver, an imitator of <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> that made Iſrael to ſinne,<note n="l" place="margin">2. Kin. 10.29</note> drawes his blade, makes it red in the bloud of the followers of <hi>Baal</hi>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">2. King 10. ver. 19. ad 28.</note>. <hi>Adramalech</hi> and <hi>Sharezer,</hi> wicked birds of an evill egge, laid violent hands on their owne father, <hi>proud Senacherib</hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">Iſa. 37.38. <hi>Reaſon ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative.</hi>
                  </note>. What truth more backed with multitude of teſtimonies, than this is? If any would know the reaſon of this, I anſwer, It is not becauſe God delights in cruelty, or takes plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to ſee men imbrue their hands in one anothers bloud; for, as<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Mac. hom. 16, 231, 236,</note> he is voide of all ſinne himſelfe, ſo hee
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18837:9"/> neither is, nor can bee the author or approver of any iniquity, notwithſtanding hee bee both the<note n="p" place="margin">Fulgent de Praedeſt. ad Monim l. 1. p. 295.296.</note> 
                  <hi>orderer</hi> and<note n="q" place="margin">Ibid.</note> avenger of it. As<note n="r" place="margin">Macar. hom. 16. p. 236.</note> 
                  <hi>no darkneſſe can comprehend his light, no impurity communicate with his holineſſe;</hi> ſo his light can abide no darkneſſe, his Majeſty can away with no wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe. The <hi>chiefeſt good</hi> cannot take pleaſure in any evill, the ſoveraigne and ſupreme Mercy cannot delight in any cruelty. He will indeed <hi>laugh at the wickeds de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and mocke when their feare commeth</hi>
                  <note n="ſ" place="margin">Pro 1.26.27.</note>: yet hee laughs not, joyes not to ſee men <hi>ſinning,</hi> in deſtroying one another. And therefore no <hi>evill</hi> or <hi>cruell diſpoſition</hi> in God, can be the ground of our aſſertion.<note n="t" place="margin">Quest.</note> What then?<note n="v" place="margin">Anſw. Reaſons af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmative. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> I anſwer, firſt his <hi>Will,</hi> ſecondly his <hi>Wiſedome;</hi> both concurring to ſet forth the glory of his Iuſtice. Firſt, his <hi>Will</hi> is the ground of it. Sinne (being the <hi>tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Law</hi>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">1. Ioh 3.16.</note>, an <hi>horrible</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">Salv. de provid Dei. l. 4. p. 120.</note> 
                  <hi>injury to his ſacred Diety,</hi> a<note n="z" place="margin">Salv. de prov. l. 1. p. 29.</note> 
                  <hi>thing that beates his eares, and knockes at heaven gates) neceſſarily calls for</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Theophyl. ad Autolyc. l. 2 p. 114. D.</note> 
                  <hi>puniſhment</hi> at the hand of his Iuſtice. Of the infliction of which puniſhment (both for the matter, manner, and <hi>meanes</hi> of it) his <hi>will</hi> is his rule. If it be his <hi>will</hi> that <hi>Angells</hi> ſhall be the inſtruments of exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting his judgements, then the deſtroying Angell is ſent forth. If it be his will that <hi>Iehu</hi> ſhall deſtroy <hi>Ahabs</hi> fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, <hi>Iehu</hi> is annointed, and appointed to the purpoſe. If it bee his will that the <hi>Daughter of Sion ſhall threſh the Nations, HER hornes ſhall be made as iron, her hooues as braſſe</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Mich. 4.13.</note>, to that worke. If on the other ſide, it be his <hi>will</hi> to give the Land of <hi>Egypt</hi> to the <hi>king of Babell,</hi> that king of Babell ſhall <hi>ſurpriſe her multitude, ſpoile her ſpoile, take her prey, and it ſhall be the wages of his Armie</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">Ezek. 29.19.</note>. It is his <hi>pleaſure</hi> to ſmite one wicked perſon by the hand of another; and therefore it is, that one evill man is puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in Gods Iuſtice, by an other as bad as himſelfe.</p>
               <p>His <hi>wiſedome,</hi> as well as his will, is another reaſon: <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> his wiſedome, I ſay, to bring to paſſe his owne worke. To puniſh the ungodly is his owne worke: Neede he aske of man or Angell what workeman he ſhall employ?
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18837:9"/> Shall the ſcholler preſcribe the Maſter what rod to ſmite with? ſhall <hi>man</hi> teach <hi>God</hi> what ſword to fight with? Hee, whoſe the <hi>Iudgement</hi> is, knowes what inſtrument to chuſe, to uſe, without the direction of any other. When therefore you ſee one wicked man ſtretching forth his hand, ſtriking with his ſword againſt another, Nation againſt Nation, as Chaldaea againſt Moab; ſay as the <hi>Prophet</hi> doth, <hi>This commeth forth from the Lord of hosts, who is wonderfull in counſell, and excellent in working</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Iſa. 28.29.</note>.</p>
               <p>A point very uſefull, if we rightly improve it. Firſt, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> 
                  <note place="margin">Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in two concluſions. Concluſion. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> it affordeth <hi>two concluſions</hi> for information of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. 1. <hi>That the warres betwixt the Pope and the Turke, are no argument that the Pope is better than the Turke.</hi> I know that Babylonian Prelate arrogates to himſelfe, as a <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority</hi> above all <hi>Princes,</hi> ſo an <hi>excellency</hi> above all <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> in the world; as though in <hi>place</hi> and <hi>grace</hi> he were <hi>ſuperior</hi> to <hi>all,</hi> inferiour to <hi>none:</hi> but, in my judgement, in <hi>baſeneſſe</hi> and <hi>badneſſe,</hi> the <hi>Turke</hi> himſelfe goes not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond him. Their curſed Kingdomes began much at the ſame time. In the yeere 607. <hi>Boniface</hi> the third, or rather <hi>Maleface,</hi> challenged by diſputes, and obtained by gifts, of that Traytor <hi>Phocas</hi> (who by murther uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped his Maſters Empire) the blaſphemous title of <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall Biſhop,</hi> juſt when <hi>Mahomet</hi> that Turkiſh Deceiver did ariſe, and aſſumed to himſelfe the proud title of a great Prophet ſent from God: So that when that<note n="e" place="margin">Vincent. Beluacenſis. l. 23. c. 39 Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condil. de Reb. Turc. l. 3. Nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cler. &amp; Danae in Auguſt. de haereſ. ca. 96.</note> 
                  <hi>Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiſh</hi> Antichriſt aroſe in the <hi>Eaſterne</hi> parts, this <hi>Popiſh</hi> Antichriſt aroſe in the <hi>Weſterne.</hi> Since which time, if either of the twaine have exceeded the other in rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries, in murthers, in whoredomes, in ſorceries, in riots, in inſolencies, in inhumanity, in maintaining their Religion by ſword and cruelty (<hi>which</hi> they <hi>could not poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly uphold by</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Vt quod ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione, &amp; hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate defendi non poterat fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rino impetu decerneretur. <hi>Savanorol. triumph. cruc. l. 4. c. 7. p. 212.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>reaſon and honeſty</hi>) it may eaſily be proved, the Pope is the man. For, 1. did<note n="g" place="margin">Vincent. Specul. hiſt. l 23. c. 41.</note> 
                  <hi>theeviſh Mahomet</hi> ever rob his owne Churches, as did<note n="h" place="margin">Platin. in Bonifac.</note> 
                  <hi>Boniface</hi> the ſeventh, who robbed <hi>Peters</hi> in Rome of all the Iewels &amp; precious things hee could finde in it? Did<note n="i" place="margin">Vincent. Spec. hiſt. l. 23. c. 41.</note> 
                  <hi>murtherous Mahomet</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:18837:10"/> ever ſlay ſo many of his Idolatrous Clergy, as did<note n="k" place="margin">Ben. Card.</note> 
                  <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> the ſeventh, who poiſoned ſix Popes to make hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe a way to the Papacy; as did<note n="l" place="margin">Cyprian. de Va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>era in Vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Vrbane</hi> the ſixt, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> put five of his Cardinalls into ſackes, and drowned them, becauſe they favoured <hi>Clement</hi> the ſeventh? which did<note n="m" place="margin">Hinc ori<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> ſchiſma peſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum, ſeu ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>2.</hi> omnium ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>matum quae ante fue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>um, &amp; ſubtiliſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum. <hi>Werner. Faſcicul. tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>por. fol 86.</hi>
                  </note> breed the moſt peſtilent ſchiſme (as their owne Writers record) that ever was in the Romane Church before. We reade of a<note n="n" place="margin">Euthym. Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaben. in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lench. Iſmae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit.</note> Dove that <hi>Mahomet</hi> had, which hee made the people beleeve was the holy Ghoſt, which came to reveale things unto him; and by that tricke gate fame to himſelfe amongſt the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar: But wee never heard of any devices hee had, by compact with the Devill, to helpe himſelfe to prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; as did<note n="o" place="margin">Platin. vit. Pontif. edit. in octav. Pariſ. an. 1555. fol. 154.</note> 
                  <hi>Silveſter</hi> the ſecond, who by ſorcery and bribery, gate the Biſhopricke of <hi>Ravenna,</hi> the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopricke of <hi>Rhemes,</hi> and the Popedome of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mahomet</hi> was uncleane and inceſtuous, but there have beene <hi>Popes</hi> which have beene more filthy in this kinde; as <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt, who (for <hi>Mahomets</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Ludov. viv. de verit. fidei l. 4. p. 487.</note> one) had<note n="q" place="margin">Onuphr. in Alexand 6.</note> ſix baſtards at the leaſt: and Pope <hi>Nicholas</hi> the third, who had a childe by a Concubine, with haire and nailes like a Bear, as their owne hiſtories report<note n="r" place="margin">Cyprian. de Valer. in Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chol. 3.</note>: And<note n="ſ" place="margin">Huldric. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtan. <hi>vel po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> Voluſian. Carthagin in Epiſt. ad Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chol. 1.</note> many others of them, who have no leſſe than broke out into <hi>unnaturall luſts,</hi> even ſuch as the Apoſtle ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.27.</p>
               <p>As touching <hi>inſolency</hi> and cruelty to uphold their Kingdomes by, there is no compariſon betwixt them<note n="t" place="margin">Lud. viv. de verit. Fid. l. 4. p. 489.</note>: <hi>Mahomet</hi> acknowledged himſelfe farre inferiour to Moſes and Chriſt; the <hi>Pope</hi>
                  <note n="v" place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.</note> exalteth himſelfe above all that is called God: ſuffering <hi>himſelfe</hi> to bee called<note n="x" place="margin">Extravag. cum Inter. Ioan. 22.</note> the <hi>Lord God;</hi> his<note n="y" place="margin">Sacr. Cerem. lib. 2. ſect. 7. c. 6. fol. 85. edit. Colon. in octavo.</note> Apoſtolicall ſeate, the <hi>ſeate of God;</hi> and the<note n="z" place="margin">Ibid. fol. 84. 86.</note> ſword which hee gives ſome Prince or other, on Chriſtmas day, the <hi>Signe</hi> of that power which hee hath in heaven and earth, and to rule from ſea to ſea, to the ends of the world.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:18837:10"/>
               <p>The <hi>one</hi> threatned but confiſcation of goods, capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity of wife, bondage of children, or loſſe of temporall life, to them that would not beleeve his writings, nor confeſſe him to bee a Prophet ſent from God: The <hi>other</hi> damneth with curſes, to the pit of hell, the <hi>ſoules</hi> of all thoſe, who doe either oppoſe his power, which is a u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped power, or gaine-ſay his Canons, which are (for the moſt of them) contrary to truth, full of blaſphemy. I liſt not any longer to warble upon this ſtring: you have heard the harmony betwixt them both, and that <hi>Turkiſh Deceiver</hi> to bee inferiour in villany (if not for kinde, yet for degree) to this <hi>Romiſh Impoſtor.</hi> Now then, if <hi>Mahomet</hi> himſelfe, who is branded in ſtory for a moſt vicious, profane, profligate fellow, for a traytor, for a man of bloud, for an whoremonger, for an idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for a deceiver, for a blaſphemer, (making God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the author of his cruelty, a pandar for his impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, the founder of his idolatry, and the authorizer of all his impiety) and for all kinde of wickedneſſe, what not? If <hi>hee,</hi> even <hi>hee,</hi> I ſay, came behinde ſome <hi>Popes</hi> in ſome curſed practiſes, why ſhould this man of ſinne <hi>now,</hi> (whoſe myſtery of iniquity workes every yeere more dangerouſly than other) challenge to himſelfe, or have given him by his Paraſites, a priority in goodneſſe before thoſe Turkiſh Emperors (<hi>Mahomets</hi> ſucceſſors) who have beene juſter, chaſter, milder, and every way better than ever <hi>Mahomet</hi> was? I goe not about to exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate the Turkes wickedneſſe in the leaſt meaſure; for they are a profane ſeede, a viperous brood, utter ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to the Croſſe of Chriſt, differing from Chriſtians both in religion and manners: But I onely enquire, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what ground it can bee proved, that the <hi>Turke</hi> is worſe than the <hi>Pope;</hi> ſome of his owne Popiſh faction having not knowne what to make of him, affirming him to be<note n="a" place="margin">Clementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narum. lib. 1. proem. fol. 3. col. 1. Gloſ. lit. K.</note> 
                  <hi>neither God, nor yet a man, a certaine wonderfull thing, &amp; ſtupor mundi, monſter</hi> of the world as I interpret it. If they ſay, that the Romane Popes have alwayes
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:18837:11"/> been at open enmity with the Turkes; have warred up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, ſometimes gotten the day of them<note n="b" place="margin">As did Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedict the eighth Platin. in vit. Pontif. fol. 157. And Clemens the ſeventh. anno 1532. Sleidan. comment. l. 8. fol. 128. edit. in 16. <hi>Concluſion</hi> 2.</note>: and therefore they are better; the doctrine in hand doth argue the inſufficiency of that argument. For, were the <hi>Chaldaeans</hi> ever a whit better than the <hi>Moabites,</hi> becauſe they were Gods inſtruments to deſtroy Moab? <hi>Evill</hi> men may quarrell, two parties may cut the throates of one another, and the beſt of them both be ſtarke naught. This is the firſt Concluſion.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is this, That it is as lawfull a thing to preſſe the <hi>bad,</hi> for Military ſervice in times of warre, as to employ the good; yea, in the ordinary ſervice of <hi>common</hi> ſouldiers, I doubt not it may ſtand as well with true piety, as State-policy, to ſpend the worſt firſt, and ſpare the beſt to the laſt extremity: albeit, it is to bee wiſhed, that <hi>none</hi> might goe forth but under <hi>good Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours,</hi> and <hi>religious Commanders.</hi> Warre in it ſelfe is a puniſhment for ſinne<note n="c" place="margin">Levit. 26.24.25.</note>. As it comes <hi>from our luſts</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Iam. 4.1.</note>, ſo it comes <hi>for our lusts.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>Culpam ſanguineo ſequitur Bellona flagello.</q>
               <p>It is well obſerved by one (commenting upon the two firſt verſes of the third chapter of Iudges,) that<note n="e" place="margin">Fer. in Iud. p. 391.</note> 
                  <hi>ſo long</hi> as the Iſraelites kept covenant with God, they had no neede of <hi>armes;</hi> but after they had once broken co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with him, and ſinned againſt him, they are faine to <hi>learne</hi> the <hi>art,</hi> and <hi>try</hi> the <hi>fortune</hi> of warre. And ſome have ſuppoſed that Mars was feigned by the Poets, to be the God of warre, becauſe he did firſt invent wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons, ſet men in battell aray, and execute other warre-like exploites, juſt at ſuch times as hee was intended to puniſh the wicked. Now if warre bee a puniſhment for ſinne, who fitter to taſte it, than the lewdeſt men, that moſt deſerve it? Againe, warre may prove a meanes to make men better. I confeſſe, we ordinarily ſee the con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rary true, <hi>that followers of the field, are no followers of the faith;</hi> and amongſt common ſouldiers, you ſhall eaſily finde the corrupteſt men, <hi>to</hi>
                  <note n="f" place="margin">Lud. viv in Epiſt. ad Henr. 8. Angl. Reg.</note> 
                  <hi>whom it is a ſport, to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18837:11"/> deſtroy houſes, to rob Churches, to raviſh virgins, to ruinate cities;</hi> yea <hi>whoſe principall glory is to doe good to</hi> no <hi>man, to hurt</hi> all <hi>men, without all regard of God, the Iudge of the whole world; who carry ſuch blinde ſoules in filthy bodies, as that they can neither feare the indignation of God, nor heare with patience the admonitions of men, bidding the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty to depart from them, ſaying, Wee deſire not the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of thy Wayes,</hi> as though <hi>they were to be ordered by no rule, to bee conformable to no right, but had licenſe to carry all lawes with their ſwords in their ſheaths, and to doe what ever their wicked hearts led them to.</hi> I confeſſe, I ſay, all this to be true; yet notwithſtanding, through Gods bleſſing<note n="g" place="margin">Providentia divina ſolet corruptos ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum mores bellis emenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. <hi>Aug. de civ. Dei l. 1. c. 1. tom. 5.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>warre</hi> may be, and indeed is a meanes to amend ſome,<note n="h" place="margin">Ariſt. de Rep. l. 8. c. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>to make them just, ſober, chaſt, good, whereas peace makes them wanton, wicked, intemperate, growne over with the ruſt of idleneſſe, and ſo ſlaves to all kinde of naughtineſſe.</hi> And is it not pity, that one ſoule ſhould bee loſt for lacke of <hi>any</hi> meanes, which may doe it good? If the daily feare and danger of death, which is ſtirred up in a wicked man (if he be not deſperately ſecure) when hee is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Pikes, may ſtir him up, to lay about him for a better life, and ſo availe to ſave his ſoule; it were a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pities he ſhould not ſee the Pikes, nor bee ſent to field. I ſpeake this the rather, that I may incite ſuch as have the office of preſſing in theſe needfull times, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto them, to be carefull to cleanſe the City, and rid the Country as much as may bee of thoſe ſtragling vagrants, loytering fellowes, and lewd livers (ſo they be fit for ſervice) which doe ſo ſwarme amongſt us. It is a great deale fitter for themſelves, and better for our Kingdome, that they be watching in garriſon, exerciſing armes, and fighting in field for our friends, againſt our enemies, than ranging our ſtreetes, haunting our ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernes, tipling in our tap-houſes, fidling in faires, jet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on ſtages, and lying like burthens upon the ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of our <hi>State;</hi> yea (which is worſe) daring the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty to his very face, and pulling downe with both
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18837:12"/> hands as faſt as they can, his heavie judgements upon the whole Nation. If it be demanded, how can a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing bee expected upon the ſervice of ſuch ſouldiers? how can wee looke that the worke of the Lord ſhould proſper in ſuch ſinnefull hands? You have an anſwer in the point we are upon, <hi>The Lord ſmiteth one wicked man by the hand of another.</hi> It cannot bee denyed that wee have cauſe to bee grieved, that ſome of them who are gone already, have carried along with them the guilt of ſuch outrages as they committed in ſome countries of our owne, which they paſſed through; and I know wee have juſt reaſon to feare, that <hi>ſome</hi> of them (at leaſt) ſhall ſoundly pay for that their wickedneſſe: yet wee have as good ground to hope, that their violence at home, ſhall bee no hinderance to <hi>Gods</hi> cauſe abroad, from proſpering, from prevailing; eſpecially, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that we have <hi>Ioſhuah's</hi> and <hi>Gideons</hi> in our <hi>Armies,</hi> and a legion of prayers, like an armed band, daily ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving with the <hi>Lord of Hoſts,</hi> that hee would bee pleaſed not to remember <hi>their</hi> ſinnes to <hi>our</hi> judgement, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be mindefull of his owne covenant, and merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to his owne inheritance. Let this ſerve for the firſt uſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Vſe <hi>2.</hi> Terror to the wicked.</note>Secondly, let terror to the wicked bee another uſe: Had paſſionate <hi>Ieremy</hi> uttered this Text in Moabs hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, I doe imagine it would have made <hi>her</hi> eares tingle, and <hi>her</hi> heart tremble, to conſider that the <hi>Chaldaeans</hi> are ſummoned by ſo terrible, ſo forcible an argument, to take <hi>ſword</hi> againſt her. Why ſhould not our preſent doctrine worke the like effect of horror and trembling in all thoſe amongſt us, who are like to Moab, <hi>godleſſe, graceleſſe,</hi> and <hi>malicious</hi> men, when it doth ſo plainely tell them, that God can plague them by <hi>wicked</hi> men, as bad <hi>as,</hi> yea perhaps many degrees worſe <hi>than</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? Should the Lord arme the <hi>Elements</hi> againſt them, which are ſo needfull, ſo uſefull to man? Should hee bid the aire infect them with a noiſome peſtilence, the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18837:12"/> drowne them by overflowing her bankes, the fire burne them by tranſgreſſing its bounds, the heavens to deny them their influence, the earth her foyzen, it were a terrible thing. To command wilde <hi>beaſts</hi> to devoure them, the Bear to teare them, the Lyon to rent them, the Loapard to prey upon them; were <hi>more</hi> terrible. Should he command his <hi>Angells,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Baſil. Seleuc. orat. 5. p. 42.</note> who <hi>(hating ſinne with an intenſtine hatred)</hi> are ready to ſmite <hi>the hairy ſcalpe</hi> of <hi>any one,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cae ſarii dial. 1 inter opera Naz. p. 1104.</note> that goes on with an impenitent heart in impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous courſes: Should the Lord (I ſay) command <hi>them</hi> to be <hi>as a</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Surgeons knife, or an Husbandmans tooles, to cut them off, to root them out (like infectious members from the body of mankinde, like ſuperfluous branches from his Vine, like noyſome weedes from the Garden of his Church)</hi> were more terrible, more unendurable; But to make <hi>wicked men</hi> the inſtruments of executing his wrath upon the children of wrath, I am not able to expreſſe how <hi>excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly more</hi> fearefull <hi>this</hi> is. When the Prophet <hi>David</hi> did pray againſt his ſlanderous enemies under the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Iudas,</hi> he begins his imprecations thus;<note place="margin">Pſal. 109.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Set thou a WICKED man over him, and let Satan ſtand at his right hand.</hi> It ſeemes, he thought he could not wiſh a greater judgement againſt his adverſaries (but one, <hi>viz.</hi> a deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very over into the Devills hands) than to have ſome <hi>wicked</hi> man their tormentor: and when there was no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy, but that <hi>himſelfe</hi> muſt be ſcourged for his ſinne of numbring the people,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 24.14.</note> and the Lord in mercy offered him his choice of three rods, he choſe rather to fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of that living God, who is a <hi>conſuming fire,</hi> than into the hands of <hi>man.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heb. 12.29.</note> Which choice he would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have made, had he not known, that wheras the juſtice of God is a mercifull juſtice, the mercies of the wicked are cruell.<note place="margin">Prov. 12.10.</note> Moab had better a thouſand times have had the people of God come armed againſt her, than a people ſo godleſſe, ſo mercileſſe as the Chaldaeans were, to bee called upon to take ſword againſt her. So thou hadſt bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter have any of the reſt of the creatures againſt thee,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18837:13"/> than a wicked man, and <hi>more mercy mayest thou meete with at its hands.</hi> An <hi>infected aire</hi> may be corrected, an <hi>unbounded fire</hi> may be quenched, <hi>overſwelling waters</hi> may be aſſwaged, <hi>devouring beaſts</hi> may be reſtrayned, yea, by the prayer of a <hi>Moſes,</hi> by the zeale of a <hi>Phineas</hi> the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying <hi>Angell</hi> may be appeaſed; but the rage of the wicked is unreaſonable, unſatiable: What mercy canſt thou looke for from him, at <hi>whoſe hands Chriſt himſelfe doth ſtill ſuffer many injuries, much ignominy and reproach?</hi> yea, who is an adverſary to himſelfe, as <hi>every wicked man is?</hi> Thou mayeſt be ſure that hee, who is led about of ſo many luſts, will not ceaſe to lay upon thee, what <hi>pride, malice, envie, hatred, covetouſneſſe,</hi> (ſuch mercileſſe maſters and commanders) ſhall command him, if thou beeſt but once (in Gods juſtice to avenge thy wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) left unto ſuch an executioner. Tremble there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and ſinne no more with ſo high an hand, you proud preſumptuous offenders: for it is a fearefull thing to fall into the hands of a wicked man, whoſe juſtice is iniquity, and whoſe very charity is cruelty it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe <hi>3.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort.</note>Thirdly, this may comfort us, and ſtrengthen our confidence, in the certainty of their overthrow, who are profeſſed enemies to Gods people. For rather than <hi>ſuch</hi> ſhall eſcape ruine without repentance, the Lord will arme their owne ſide againſt them, and make men, as wicked as themſelves, inſtruments of executing his judgements upon them. It was for <hi>Iſraels</hi> comfort (as <hi>Calvin</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Calv. in Ier. c. 48 v. 10.</note> obſerveth upon the Text) that <hi>Ieremy</hi> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told <hi>Moabs</hi> overthrow by the <hi>Chaldaeans</hi> ſword. In like manner propound to your ſelves this point out of <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> words, to <hi>your</hi> comfort; and aſſure your ſelves, that although the enemies of Sion bee many and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant, powerfull and politick, yet <hi>deliverance ſhall come:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Heſt. 4.14.</note> and rather than that Romiſh Whore ſhall <hi>alwaies</hi> continue to ſucke the bloud of Gods Saints, ſome <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh</hi> power, ſome <hi>Pagan</hi> Idolater ſhall ſoake his blade
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18837:13"/> in her bloud, and her ſouldiers and followers ſhall one day finde, how like a Prophet one of their ſide once ſpake, when he ſaid, <hi>Oh you Romaniſts,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lud Viv. de vit. ſub Turc. pag. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>who love your li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, and ſtand much upon your immunities, thinke with your ſelves, how baſe, how poore, how diſhonourable, how ſlaviſh a life you are like to lead under Paganiſh enemies, who will uſe you like beaſts, rather than men: which hard condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhall be Gods juſt vengeance upon you,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Id. Ibid. p. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>for your cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty againſt his Church, of which you doe profeſſe your ſelves members.</hi> And ſo let us leave the firſt point of the the ſecond part of our Text, and come to the ſecond, which ſtands thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>That the ſword muſt not be ſtretched out to bloud,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Doct. <hi>3.</hi> The ſword must keep ſcab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard, untill it be called forth, and hath a good warrant to ſtrike.</note> 
                  <hi>without a juſt cauſe, and a good call.</hi> The ſword may not drink bloud without warrant. The holy Ghoſt doth not ſay here, <hi>Curſed be hee that putteth not out</hi> his ſword <hi>to</hi> bloud before he be called, but, Curſed be he that <hi>holdeth backe</hi> his ſword <hi>from</hi> bloud, when hee is willed and warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to dip it, to dye it in the ſame. <hi>David</hi> had neither call, nor cauſe to beſmeare his ſword with <hi>Vriah's</hi> bloud, and how great a ſinne hee did commit, who knowes not, that knowes the ſtory, or hath but heard how God chaſtized him according as hee told him, that the <hi>ſword ſhould never depart from his houſe?</hi> how <hi>Nathan</hi> reproved him, <hi>Thou art the man,</hi> and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe cryed <hi>peccavi</hi> for it?<note place="margin">2. Sam. 12.7.10.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Doeg</hi> had no call from God to ſlay in one day foureſcore and five of the Lords Prieſts, and how hainous and unlawfull a fact that was, both the refuſall of <hi>Sauls</hi> ſervants to doe it,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 22.17.18. Pſal. 52.1.2. 1. King. 22.37.</note> though their maſter commanded them, and <hi>Davids</hi> juſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, and crying out againſt him, doe declare. Had not <hi>Ahab</hi> ill ſucceſſe, when he went up to battell againſt <hi>Ramoth Gilead</hi> againſt Gods will? Did it not coſt that good king <hi>Ioſiah</hi> his life,<note place="margin">2. Chr. 35.22.23. Iohn 18.11. Matth. 26.52. Stel. in Luc. c. 22.</note> when hee would needs draw out his ſword againſt <hi>Pharaoh Necho</hi> king of Egypt, without Gods warrant, yea contrary to Gods word in <hi>Pharaohs</hi> mouth? When <hi>Peter</hi> pulled out his ſword, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18837:14"/> cut off the high Prieſts ſervants eare, our Saviour bade him put up againe, telling him plainely, that he that did ſmite with the ſword, ſhould periſh by the ſword. By which ſpeech, he did not <hi>ſo much hinder Peter for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,</hi> from a good action, <hi>which he might do</hi> (as one thinks) but he <hi>reproved him,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. in Iohan. tract. 11<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>and tooke him up roundly for what hee had done.</hi> Now wherefore did hee reprehend him? What?<note place="margin">Eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hym. in Mat. c. 56. fol. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>67.</note> becauſe it is never lawfull for any man to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend Gods cauſe with the ſword, as ſome have thought? No. Why then? becauſe <hi>Peters</hi> fleſhly and unregenerate part did raſhly ruſh upon this action, without any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to his Maſters will, without any warrant from his Maſters call: which planely argues, that the <hi>ſmiting with the ſword without a call, was not permitted by Christ to Peter,</hi> nor any other. I hope you doe not expect ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny arguments for this, when one or two may ſerve for all.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> 1. Actions of this nature, tend to the taking away of naturall life. Now life is ſo precious to the bruit crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>that it ſtrives to preſerve it how it can;</hi> how much <hi>more</hi> precious is the life of <hi>man,</hi> by which man himſelfe enjoyes many excellent benefits, and the God of heaven gets much honour? Therefore we had need be ſure that we have ſpeciall cauſe, before we venture upon a work that takes away the life of ſuch a creature as man is, leſt we raſhly entrench ſo farre upon Gods honour, and ſo wrongfully cut off man from the poſſeſſion of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing enjoyed by life, as we will never be able to anſwer. For mans life is never to be extinguiſhed, but when it is an hinderance to Gods glory, and altogether hurtfull to humane ſociety; and not <hi>then</hi> neither, but by ſuch as are appointed by God to that worke.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>2</label> 2. The ſtretching out the ſword to bloud, requires the putting on of a kinde of cruelty; as we ſee in <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muell,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.33. Ioſ. 10.26.</note> who hewed <hi>Agag</hi> in pieces without any ſhew of compaſſion; as we ſee in <hi>Ioſhuah,</hi> who hanged up the five Heatheniſh kings without any commiſeration.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:18837:14"/> Now wee know, that the Scripture doth every where almoſt call upon us for the <hi>contrary;</hi> to be mercifull, to put upon our ſelves the <hi>bowels of tender compaſſion,</hi> to cloath our ſelves with goodneſſe, with kindneſſe, to doe good to all, to love our enemies. And therefore we had need have a ſpeciall care, that we have a ſpeciall call to put this habite upon us, leſt wee exerciſe a lawleſſe cruelty, when, and where we ſhould ſhew lawfull mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; and leſt when wee ſhould compaſſionately ſpare the effuſion of bloud, wee doe unadviſedly ſpill it, and by that meanes bring upon our owne heads the guilt of bloud: which is a very fearefull and heavie thing.</p>
               <p>This is a doctrine I doe deſire may bee remembred by our reverend Iudges, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> when being ſet in their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſeates, the <hi>lives</hi> of men are brought in queſtion before them: Oh what good may it make them doe, what evill may it keepe them from! how may it make them rid the innocent out of the bloud-hunters clawes, and ſet them free from the hands of thoſe wretches, whoſe falſe tongues (a bloud-thirſty deſire, ariſing from malicious covetouſneſſe) doe ſet on worke to give in evidence againſt them! Would they but conſider at <hi>that</hi> time, that the ſword of juſtice muſt not touch the bloud of any man, without a juſt and important cauſe; oh what prayers would they make to God to guide them! what paines will they take in ſifting of cauſes, in ſounding of witneſſes, in examining of evidences, in boulting out all appendant circumſtances, that they will not paſs ſentence upon the party, except he be worthy of death indeed? or if they do, the fault ſhall be more in the Iurors, than in any negligence in themſelves to ſearch the truth, or want of conſcience to paſſe ſentence, as out of the ſeate, and in the ſight of God himſelfe. I touch but upon this ſtring;<note place="margin">Iſocr. Epiſt. 2. p. 803. A cont. praefat. affix. ſtratag. Satan.</note> I have more pertinent uſes to apply my ſelfe unto. The firſt whereof I feare mee will be harſh, becauſe, (as that Orator told <hi>Philip,</hi> great <hi>Alexanders</hi> father) <hi>men love rather to be praiſed than re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved.</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:18837:15"/> But if I be harſh, I muſt crave pardon: a two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold evill, too common in our times. A groſſe error in ſome, a raſh practiſe in others, doe neceſſarily call for a juſt reproofe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Vſe <hi>2.</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold. <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note>The error is, that to give the ſtabbe for a croſſe word, or to challenge the field upon every ſlender occaſion, is a ſigne of true fortitude: and that hee is a baſe gull, no rightly valorous, nor magnanimous Gentleman, that will pocket up the leaſt injury, and not proſecute it to the very drawing of bloud from him that offers it. Of theſe erroneous ſpirits and furious ſparkes, I would gladly know, what proofes they can give, that true va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour conſiſteth in ſuch exploits, what call men have to expreſſe their fortitude by ſuch private quarrells. Is the thwarting of their humour, the ſtirring of their choler a call ſufficient, cauſe warrantable enough? they want grace or wit if once they thinke it. Now Duells without a call to them, are <hi>lawleſſe</hi> things; and did ever any man, <hi>Divine</hi> or Pagan, teach and avouch that <hi>lawleſſe</hi> things are truely praiſe-worthy? There are ſome enemies I confeſſe, whoſe bloud to ſhed is a very laudable action; but in heate of bloud to ſhed Chriſtian bloud, is a condemnable vice in the eyes of God, yea, what is further from true fortitude, than this is? <hi>The magnitude of the minde is proved by this, that it is capable of eternity</hi> (as a <hi>Father</hi> ſpeaketh);<note place="margin">Bern. in Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tic. ſer 80.</note> not by this, that it ſcorneth to put up the pettieſt injury. True valour con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in <hi>patience</hi> and <hi>humility,</hi> not in anger or unbridled fury. For men to dog one another to the field, that they may wreake their wrath the one upon the other, and take away life the one from the other, is a manifeſt badge of a <hi>baſe</hi> minde, an evident token of a <hi>villanous</hi> ſpirit; and dare any applaude it for a marke and ſigne of a brave courage and valiant ſpirit?<note place="margin">Baſil. Seleu. orat. 5 p. 38.</note> Oh applauſe (as one ſaid once on occaſion of <hi>Cains</hi> churliſh anſwer to God, <hi>Am I my brothers keeper?</hi>) Oh voice more execrable than the murther it ſelfe! oh impious and irreligious ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence!
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18837:15"/> This is to juſtifie wickedneſſe it ſelfe, this is to applaude the manifeſt breach of the ſixth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in a hainous kinde. To ſtretch out the ſword <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> God <hi>commands,</hi> to ſtrike with the ſword <hi>when</hi> God <hi>forbids,</hi> call you <hi>this</hi> true Valour? Valour! it is (as <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. in Pſal. 58. To 8.</note> ſaies of confidence in mans owne merits) a <hi>mad va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour</hi> then, a <hi>reproveable,</hi> a <hi>damnable valour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What? <hi>A damnable valour,</hi> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label> when men irritate and provoke one another by reproaches, by diſgraces, by other kinde of wrongs?</p>
               <p>Yes, even <hi>then,</hi> a damnable valour, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> or rather <hi>Cowar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize:</hi> For he is conquered by his angry paſſions, like a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, that falls to fighting for a few reproaches; and it is a fooliſh thing to account a perſon a man of courage, who like a vanquiſhed ſlave, lies proſtrate at the feet of the luſt of anger. Tell me I pray, did not <hi>David</hi> doe a more noble exploit by bearing with patience the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of <hi>Shimei,</hi> than hee ſhould have done if hee had drawne his ſword and ſlaine him with it? To lay ſnares for bloud, for a few croſſe words, is a greater injury, than thoſe croſs words can be: &amp; a thouſand times bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it is, <hi>injuriam ferre, quàm inferre,</hi> to <hi>ſuffer</hi> wrong,<note place="margin">Baſil. Seleu. orat. ult. p. 407. Aug. in pſa. 92.</note> than <hi>offer</hi> it, to <hi>beare</hi> the <hi>leſſer,</hi> than <hi>doe</hi> the <hi>greater:</hi> At <hi>this bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> thine anger ſhall breake and ſplit in pieces, thy courage, thy ſtrength ſhall hold its owne. For, hee is a man of mettall indeede, who can generouſly beare all adverſe accidents. Had but ſuch challenges a good end, were ſuch ſingle combates, which are more grounded on malice, than on the law of Armes, uſefull or gaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in their <hi>iſſue,</hi> there were ſome reaſon to commend them. But their fruite and iſſue being for the moſt part ſo fearefull, ſo woefull,<note place="margin">Bern in ſerm. ad milit. Templ. cap. 2. fol. 83. Q.</note> that the <hi>ſlayer committeth a deadly ſinne, the party ſlaine</hi> (without Gods greater mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ey) <hi>is ſent to hell,</hi> thou art to bee condemned, if thou doeſt not condemne them.</p>
               <p>It may be objected, the victor gets glory by his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, and gaines a name to be the better champion. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
                  </label>
               </p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:18837:16"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> 
                  <note place="margin">Eraſ. Enchirid. mil Chriſt. p. 136. 137.</note>A ſory glory, God wot, that being true which <hi>Eraſmus</hi> writeth, <hi>That to bee praiſed for ſinnefull things of ſinne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full men, is falſe glory, and true ignominy.</hi> Reforme thine error therfore here worthily taxed, whoever thou beeſt, that thinkeſt thoſe men the braveſt ſparkes, whoſe wounding ſwords a petty injury can call forth to take revenge, without a call from God; leſt, if this error ſtickes to thee ſtill, thou falleſt like <hi>Cain,</hi> upon the leaſt provocation, to imbrue thy hands in thy brothers bloud: and when thou haſt done it, be ſo farre from repenting, as to conteſt with God as <hi>Cain</hi> did, <hi>and out of thine envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, malicious, and hatefull heart, rather to grieve that thy murthered brother</hi> hath not another life for thee to take away alſo. Which paſſe ſhouldeſt thou ever come unto, a remarkeable horror might take hold upon thee, a guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty conſcience ever vexe thee, the gnawing whereof, death it ſelfe (though thou ſhouldeſt deſire it) would rather encreaſe by infinite degrees, than eaſe in the leaſt meaſure.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Branch of reproofe.</note>Secondly, there is a generation amongſt us, who in ſuch troubleſome times as theſe be, ſteale from their Parents, runne from their Maſters, tendering their ſervice, to take ſword in hand, when they have neither wit to weild it, nor ſtrength to fight with it: the ſhop or the ſchoole, being fitter for them, than the field. <hi>Their</hi> raſhneſſe alſo doth this doctrine reach at (for they are old enough to heare a reproofe.) Silly yonguelings, they doe inconſiderately venture on they know not what. Where is their warrant to runne to warre? The ſword muſt not kill, till it hath a call. <hi>Dulce bellum inexpertis,</hi> Warre is ſweete untill they have taſted of it. When they heare the Cannons roare, the Armour clatter, the Ayre thunder, the Launces ſhiver, the Heavens reſound with hideous out-cries of parties ſlaine; when they ſee the Swords glittering, the Pikes piercing; one with a leg off, another without an arme; one lye ſcrambling on the earth on this ſide, another lye tumbling in bloud on
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:18837:16"/> that ſide the enemies looking fiercely, ſtriking furiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, doubling blowes upon them, threatning death unto them, were there no more men in the world than them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; then peradventure (wanting the fortitude which the field requireth) they wil repent their raſhneſſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Campus fortem poſtulat.</hi> En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod. Panegyr. Theoderico Regi. pag. 318.</note> wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they had waited for a better call, &amp; not ſo theeviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtole away. I taxe not Voluntaries who are fit for ſervice; I blame not them that have a call: but I finde fault with ſuch as in a diſcontented, or new fangled hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, will venture upon the pikes, being altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, unfit to beare armes; whoſe ſtay at home would bee a great deale more acceptable to God, more profitable to man. <hi>He that fightes without aſound, is no ſouldier;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chryſol. ſerm. 14. p. 58.</note> 
                  <hi>wrath carries him to valour; his adventure is perillous, not vertuous; he ſeekes rather to periſh than to vanquiſh, as one ſpeakes.</hi> Did an<note n="*" place="margin">Dion. Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſt. orat. 38.</note> heathen man once moſt juſtly complayne againſt the Nicomedians, becauſe for Peſtilence and Earthquakes they did accuſe their gods; but for ſtirring up to warre, they did applaude their <hi>men:</hi> accounting the perſwaders to battell the beſt Orators, when to uſe ſuch perſwaſions too there was neither need nor cauſe? with better war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant may I blame ſuch yongulings as account thoſe men moſt worthy to be hearkned to who egg and entice them into the field when (as having neither skill nor ſtrength to uſe their weapons for lack of yeeres) they are like to be more burthenous, than helpfull to the armie. If they periſh by the ſword, they doe but reape the fruit of their owne raſhnes. And now enough of reproofe.</p>
               <p>Thirdly &amp; laſtly, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> muſt not the ſword be commanded to bloud without a call? then uſe the meditation of this truth for thy defence, when at any time thou art eyther provoked by gaine or malice, to lay violent hands upon thy brother, or tempted in diſcontent, <hi>Saul</hi>-like to runne thy ſelfe upon thyne own ſword. To <hi>neither</hi> of theſe haſt thou a <hi>call;</hi> to doe <hi>either</hi> of theſe is a greivous ſinne. For the firſt of theſe, what ſaies the Scipture?<note place="margin">Gen. 9.6. 1. Ioh. 3.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Who ſo ſheddeth mans bloud, by man ſhall his bloud be ſhed. The murderer hath
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:18837:17"/> not eternall life abiding in him.</hi> He that takes away his <hi>bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> life, may heare God tell him, The <hi>voyce</hi> of thy bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers bloud cryeth from off the earth againſt thee. <hi>Vitam ſuſtuliſti,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Baſil Seleue. orat. 5. pag. 38. 39.</note> 
                  <hi>ſed non vocem abſtuliſti. Thou hast ſpilt his life, but thou canſt not ſtop his mouth; thou haſt armed his bloud as an accuſer againſt thee, thou haſt provoked the immortall God to be an adverſary unto thee.</hi> Some ſuch noyſe as this may ſound in his eares, which is moſt hideous, horrid, and fearefull to heare. To the latter very aptly ſpeakes an Ancient,<note place="margin">Aug. in Ioh. cap. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>By how much the neerer to a man the murthered is, by ſo much the crueller is the murtherer.</hi> He therefore that murthereth himſelfe, is the worſt murtherer, becauſe none is neerer to a man than himſelfe. <hi>Iob</hi> reſolved to waite all the dayes of his appointed time, untill his changing came. Hee made not poſt-haſte away before his time; albeit one would thinke he had as great cauſe to have done it (had it beene lawfull) as ever any had, whether we conſider the tortures of his body, or the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of his ſoule.<note place="margin">Senec. Ep. 24.</note> The Heathen could tell us, that a good man muſt not <hi>flye</hi> out of this life, but <hi>depart</hi> out of it. Hee muſt ſtay in this world till God bid him goe; hee muſt not, like a diſcontented Tenant, warne himſelfe out of this earthly tabernacle againſt his Landlords revealed will, leſt like the fooliſh fiſh, he leape out of the pan into the fire, and ſo finde by woefull experience the truth of our preſent point, That the ſword muſt not bee dipt in any bloud without a call.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct <hi>4</hi> For the ſword to keepe ſcabbard when God calls it o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>kes his diſpleaſure, as a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> accu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ed thing.</note>And now I am deſcended to the laſt and largeſt point of all, being the very upſhot of the Text, That to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the ſword from bloud when there is juſt cauſe and a lawfull call, is a dangerous thing, diſpleaſing to God, expoſing to the Curſe.</p>
               <p>A doctrine ſet downe ſo plainely by our Prophet <hi>here,</hi> that<note n="*" place="margin">Habak. 2.2.</note> 
                  <hi>he that runnes may reade</hi> it, <hi>[Curſed be he that keepeth backe his ſword from bloud]:</hi> and backed ſo firmely by te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, by example, and by the contrary, that none but the incredulous can once doubt of it. The teſtimony is
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:18837:17"/> 
                  <hi>Deborah's</hi> in her ſong.<note place="margin">Iudg. 5.23.</note> 
                  <hi>Curſe yee Meroſh (ſaid the Angell of the Lord) Curſe yee bitterly the inhabitants thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they came not to the helpe of the Lord againſt the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie:</hi> that is to ſay,<note place="margin">Fer. in Iud. c. 5. pag. 407.</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe they kept their ſwordes in their ſheaths, when they ſhould have fought in his cauſe, for his Church.</hi> The <hi>example</hi> is <hi>Saul's,</hi> who was accurſt in his affaires, and had his kingdome rent from him, for ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the life of the King of <hi>Amalek,</hi> when God had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him a charge to cut him off.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.8.23.</note> The <hi>contrary</hi> is ſet downe by the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezech. 29.20.</note> who tells us that <hi>Nebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chadnezzar</hi> (though a wicked King) had the <hi>land</hi> of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt given him as his pay for his paines, in puniſhing the <hi>people</hi> of Egypt with his ſword, according to the command which God gave him to doe it. The rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of ſuch a worke, when it was done, with a tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall bleſſing, doth intimate, that to leave ſuch a worke undone, when the Lord calls to it, procureth the Curſe <hi>temporall</hi> at leaſt.</p>
               <p>Is not the ſtretching out the ſword to bloud ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>Gods</hi> worke? Is it not a worke as <hi>from</hi> him, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>
                  </label> ſo <hi>for</hi> him? Is not his command the ground of it? Is not the bringing of his owne counſells to paſſe (in the <hi>deſtroying</hi> of ſome to the glory of his <hi>juſtice,</hi> in the relieving of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to the praiſe of his mercy) the end of it? But to omit the worke of the <hi>Lord,</hi> is a curſed thing, (For if <hi>remiſſeneſſe</hi> in ſuch a worke (as appeares in the former part of the verſe) then much more the totall <hi>omiſſion</hi> of it, expoſeth to the Curſe.<note place="margin">Curſed be he that doth the worke of the Lord NEG<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIGENT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LY.</note>) therefore to withhold the ſword from bloud when God requires it, muſt needes be an accurſed thing. It proves impiety to ſhew pitty at ſuch a time. Mercy <hi>then</hi> is a fooliſh mercy, and hee that ſhewes it, verifies that ſaying of an heathen man, <hi>It is an hard thing to bee mercifull and wiſe at the ſame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ageſilaus apud Plut. Apopth. Moral. in tom. 2. pag. 191. Graecol. edit.</note> To bee mercifull to him whom God would have deſtroyed by the ſword, and to bee wiſe enough to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for himſelfe an eſcape from the curſe, is very diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:18837:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:18837:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:18837:19"/>
               <p>I would now apply my ſelfe to apply the point, <hi>but</hi> that I muſt firſt explaine it by the object and the motive cauſe; I meane, by anſwering two queſtions: firſt, <hi>againſt whom?</hi> ſecondly, <hi>for what?</hi> the ſword is commanded forth by God, that ſo wee may know when wee have a good call to the battell. Both which I entend to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch with as much brevity as I can.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Queſt. <hi>1.</hi> Against <hi>whom</hi> God calleth forth the ſword.</note>For the firſt: Our Text tells us, that it was Moabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh bloud which the Chaldaeans ſwordes were to bee ſheathed in; the <hi>Moabites,</hi> their enemies, were they to wage battell with, not with their owne countrimen, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies and friends. The Lord gave charge to <hi>Reheboam</hi> King of <hi>Iudah,</hi> not to make warre with <hi>Ieroboam</hi> King of <hi>Iſrael;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. King. 12.24.</note> and why? becauſe Iſrael and Iudah were ſiſters and friends. The Lord was angry with the <hi>Ephraimites,</hi> ſo that hee ſlew two and forty thouſand of them for quarrelling and contending with <hi>Iephtah</hi> their brother.<note place="margin">Iudg. 12.6.</note> Thoſe valiant <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Captaines</hi> which wee read of in Scripture, have ſtill fought with their owne, and Gods <hi>enemies;</hi> as <hi>David</hi> with the <hi>Philiſtims, Ioſuah</hi> with the <hi>Canaanites, Iehoſaphat</hi> with the <hi>Moabites, Nehemiah</hi> with the <hi>Ammonites,</hi> &amp;c. The Lord never taught their hands to warre, nor their fingers to fight, with any but ſuch as <hi>they</hi> were.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Object.</hi> Mat. 5.44. Luke 6.27.28.</note>But how ſtands this, with that counſell of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, <hi>Love your enemies, bleſſe them that curſe you, pray for them that perſecute you?</hi> Is to warre with them, to love them? Is to joine battell with them, to bleſſe them?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> I anſwer: Firſt of all what hindereth but that a man may love his enemies while hee combates with them, when his fighting with them proceedes rather from hatred to their ſinne, than from want of love to their perſon?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>2</label> Secondly, I give no juſt occaſion to move this obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: For I doe not ſay, that God doth <hi>alwaies</hi> call a man to wage warre with his enemies; but when the ſword is called forth, <hi>it must</hi> know our <hi>foes,</hi> not our
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:18837:19"/> 
                  <hi>friends,</hi> for the object of its ſtroakes. <hi>Bernard</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bern. ſerm ad Milit. Templ. c. 3. f. 83. col. 4. li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. R.</note> ſaid well, <hi>Our very enemies are not to bee killed, if they can by any meanes elſe bee curbed from infesting, from oppreſſing the Church; but when that cannot be, it is a great deale better, that the rod be cut with the ſword, than ſtill reſt upon the backe of the Righteous, and cauſe them to put forth their hands to iniquity.</hi> Our Lords counſell to love our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, doth no whit prejudice the juſt cauſes of warre. <hi>If the cauſe be good,</hi> neither the effect,<note place="margin">Bern. ad. Milit. Templ. ca p. 1. fol. 83. col. 4 P</note> nor <hi>iſſue can bee naught,</hi> though the bloud of thouſands bee ſpilt by it. Our next taske therefore, muſt be to give in our anſwer to the ſecond demand, <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Quest. <hi>2.</hi> What be the cauſes of a juſt warre.</note> 
                  <hi>For what cauſes</hi> the Lord gives warrant to wage warre with our foes? What? is it to give ſatisfaction to the unreaſonable motion of raſh an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger? to compaſſe that honour, that applauſe amongſt men, which wee ambitiouſly aſpire to? to get our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies poſſeſſions, which we unlawfully covet? meerly to be made Lords of Sea and of Land? or to rule by our ſelves without Competitor? I know <hi>carnall</hi> men (both amongſt<note n="a" place="margin">
                     <p>Plut. de. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſol. ad Apol. to. 2. Graecol. edit. 108. A. Saluſt in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til.</p>
                     <p>Dion. Chryſ. orat. 38. fol. 317. 318. Tul. Epiſt. Fam. l. 8. Epiſt. antepenult.</p>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Infidells</hi> and<note n="b" place="margin">Bern. ad Mil. Templ. c. 2. fol. 83. col. 4. Q.</note> Chriſtians) have in former times made warre for <hi>theſe</hi> cauſes. And at<note n="c" place="margin">Tacit. hiſt. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>this</hi> day theſe vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are to ſuch perſons, the chiefeſt bellowes to blow this fire. For what but theſe, makes <hi>Rome, Spaine,</hi> and <hi>Austria</hi> ſtirre up ſuch combuſtions, as have of late been kindled, and doe yeerely flame more and more in the Chriſtian world?</p>
               <p>But are theſe <hi>juſt</hi> cauſes?</p>
               <p>No, no, there is neither equity nor<note n="d" place="margin">Bern. ad Mil. Templ. c. 2. fol. 83.</note> ſafety in them. They are rather Robbers than Souldiers, who are led to field onely by theſe motives.</p>
               <p>What then are juſt cauſes? Such as for which Moab was to be waſted by the <hi>Chaldaean</hi> ſword. What were they?</p>
               <p>Theſe five ſinnes, as you may ſee, if you conſult but with ſome verſes in this preſent chapter.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Monſtrous pride.</item>
                  <item>2. Inſolence againſt God.</item>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:18837:20"/>
                  <item>3. Inſulting over the Church.</item>
                  <item>4. Tumultuouſneſſe and rebellion.</item>
                  <item>5. Falſe-heartedneſſe.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Which vices in other enemies as well as Moab, have been Gods warrant to his owne Worthies, to fight his battells in the old Teſtament.</p>
               <p>Firſt (I ſay) monſtrous Pride. We have heard of the pride of Moab [He is exceeding proud] even of his haughtineſſe and his pride,<note place="margin">Iſa. 16.6. Ier. 48.29.32.33.</note> his loftineſſe and arrogan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie: Therefore the ſpoiler is fallen upon thy Summer fruites, and joy and gladneſſe is taken away from the land of Moab.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Inſolence againſt God. <hi>The horne of Moab is cut off, and his arme is broken, ſaith the Lord. Make ye him drunken,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſ. 25 26.</note> 
                  <hi>for he magnified himſelfe againſt the Lord. Moab ſhall be deſtroyed from being a people, becauſe hee magnified himſelfe againſt the Lord.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſ. 42.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, Inſulting over the Church, is another cauſe of juſt deſtruction by the ſword. <hi>Moab ſhall wallow in his vomite, and he ſhall alſo be in deriſion: For was not Iſrael a deriſion unto thee, ſince thou ſpakest of him? thou skippedst for joy.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſ. 29.27.</note> 
                  <hi>Goliah's</hi> vaunts againſt the hoſt of Iſrael, put the <hi>ſtone</hi> into <hi>Davids ſling,</hi> which pierced his temples; put the <hi>ſword</hi> into <hi>Davids hand,</hi> which parted his head from his body, and ſo diſcomfited his inſolent Army of <hi>uncircumciſed Philiſtims.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Sam. 17.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, for Tumultuouſneſſe and Rebellion, evident is that which we finde towards the end of this chapter. <hi>I will bring upon it, even upon Moab, the yeare of their viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, ſaith the Lord. A fire ſhall come forth out of Heſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bon, and a flame from the midst of Sion, which ſhall devoure the corner of Moab,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Verſ. 44.45.</note> 
                  <hi>and the crowne of the head of the TV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MVLTVOVS ones.</hi> And what was it elſe, but the ſuppreſſing of Rebellion, that moved the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to make warre upon the Beniamites?<note place="margin">Iudg. 20.12 26.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Fiftly, for Falſe-heartedneſſe; pretences of unity, and yet practiſes of enmity: you may collect it out of the 30.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:18837:20"/> verſe, where Moabs <hi>wrath</hi> and <hi>lyes</hi> are joyned together, and noted as a cauſe of the Chaldaeans comming, by Gods appointment, againſt her to deſtroy her.</p>
               <p>While I thought with my ſelfe how I might improve this point, many particulars offered themſelves: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe many, I made choice of three.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> to meete with that fantaſticall conceit of the <hi>Anabaptiſticall</hi> Sect, <hi>That it is not lawfull for true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans to make warre.</hi> Are <hi>Christians</hi> prohibited to doe that ſame thing, which if the <hi>Chaldaeans</hi> did <hi>not,</hi> they were threatned to bee curſed? What worke is there, which may lawfully bee done for the Lord, by any that are his <hi>enemies,</hi> which may not in ſome caſes, for ſome cauſes, with ſome cautions, be done by his <hi>friends?</hi> In this ſame queſtion <hi>(Whether a Chriſtian Magiſtrate may lawfully make warre?)</hi> the ſtate of it lies not in <hi>unneceſſary</hi> warre: When Kings and Princes, through an ambitious and covetous deſire to enlarge their owne territories, and to encroach upon other mens rights, without Gods war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, doe take ſword in hand, and bid battell with it; wee deteſt it, wee abhorre it, and perſwade our ſelves, that the authors of <hi>ſuch</hi> warres, have an heavie account to give to God, for the abundance of innocent bloud that is ordinarily ſhed, for the rapines, burnings, whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, devaſtations, &amp;c. which doe uſually attend them. But wee ſpeake of a <hi>neceſſary defenſive</hi> warre: When a Chriſtian Prince, partly to preſerve the lives, liberties, and religion of his owne ſubjects; partly to relieve his <hi>Allies</hi> abroad, which are neere unto him, both in the fleſh and in the Lord, when they are oppreſſed by the common adverſary, ſhall make warre, it is not onely lawfull, but alſo ſo needefull, that did hee not doe it, he ſhould highly diſpleaſe God, as being an unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall father to his country, &amp; an unkind friend to them, whom hee doth owe, and ſhould ſhew moſt kindeneſſe unto. In theſe caſes he doth not,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> he ought not to beare the ſword in vaine, what ever the Anabaptiſts ſay to
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:18837:21"/> the contrary. If wee ſhould tell that generation, that <hi>Abraham</hi> made warre with the Sodomites,<note place="margin">Gen. 14. Gen. 17. Ioſhuah <hi>paſſim.</hi> Iudg. 6. Iudg. 13.14. 15 chapters.</note> 
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> with the Amalekites, <hi>Ioſuah</hi> with the Canaanites, <hi>Gideon</hi> with the Midianites, <hi>Sampſon</hi> with the uncircumciſed Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtims; and Gods encouraging and proſpering them in this worke, is a notable argument of the lawfulneſſe of it: I know they will yeeld to us in <hi>that,</hi> holding it law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in the time of the <hi>old Testament</hi> to make warre. But where (ſay they) is it warranted in the <hi>New?</hi> Where warrented! Why where is it condemned? Doth <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> condemne it? Souldiers, <hi>military</hi> men, came to him, asked him what they ſhould doe; and what's his anſwer to them?<note place="margin">Luke 3.</note> not <hi>leave your ſtation, forſake your gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon, give over your military kinde of life;</hi> but, <hi>bee content with your wages, doe no man wrong.</hi> Neither did Chriſt, nor any of his Apoſtles, diſallow it. The Capernaite Centurion remained a ſouldier after he became a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. Chriſt did not bid him ceaſe the field, after hee had truely embraced the faith. He commended his <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matth. 8. Act. 10.</note> Verily, <hi>I have not found ſuch faith in Iſrael;</hi> hee condemned not his <hi>calling,</hi> his being a Centurion. The like may bee ſaid of <hi>Cornelius,</hi> the Captaine of the Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian band, whoſe <hi>Captaineſhip</hi> continued after his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion: neither was it condemned by <hi>Peter,</hi> when hee preached unto him, and beſtowed Baptiſme upon him.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Object.</hi> Iſa. 2.4.</note>Yea but <hi>Iſaiah</hi> propheſied of the times of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell in the new Teſtament, when he ſaid, <hi>They ſhall beate their ſwords into plow-ſheares, and their ſpeares into pruning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hookes: Nation ſhall not lift up ſword againſt Nation, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall they learne warre any more:</hi> Therefore Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans may not make warre now under the Goſpell.</p>
               <p>I anſwer, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
                  </label> the ſcope of the Prophet <hi>there,</hi> is not to forbid Magiſtrates a neceſſary warre againſt the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of their lives, and Gods cauſe: but to ſhew what peace ſhould be betwixt the Iewes and the Gentiles by the preaching of the Goſpell; which was accompliſhed when our Peace-maker,<note place="margin">Eph. 2.14.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> brake down the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:18837:21"/> wall betwixt them and us; and when, in a time of dearth, the Church of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> in <hi>Graecia</hi> did ſend reliefe, even above their power,<note place="margin">2. Cor. 8.1.</note> to the Church of the <hi>Iewes</hi> in <hi>Syria.</hi> They have many other cavills, ſcarce worth the ſpending of our inke and paper, which of purpoſe I paſſe over, leſt in ſuch an argument as this, I prove tedious to the Reader.</p>
               <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">Vſe <hi>2.</hi> Terror.</note> I may here take juſt occaſion to preach terror unto all thoſe, whom God hath indued with ſtrength of body, ſo that they might bee fit in time of neede, to ſtand their country in good ſtead, by bearing the ſword againſt her enemies; and they waſte this ſtrength and ability of theirs, ſome on wine, ſome on women, ſome by one kinde of riotous living, ſome by another, and ſo indiſpoſe themſelves for all good offices at home in peace, for all good ſervice in the warres a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad. The <hi>naturall</hi> gift which God hath given them, they ſhould <hi>perfect</hi> by <hi>art,</hi> by commendable exerciſes eyther in military matters, or ſome lawfull calling; and they, eyther by a ſottiſh idleneſſe, or a beſtiall licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, diſable themſelves to make ſuch uſe of their bodies, as they are given them for. The time may come, when God may ſummon theſe voluptuous ones to ſtretch out the ſword to bloud, yea and threaten a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them the terrible Curſe if they doe not doe it. This Curſe, how can they then eſcape, when their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, weakened by ſinne, ſhall make them refuſe to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low this call, and cauſe them to bee readier with the Kitchin-Curre that <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſpeakes of, to runne to the pot, than with the generous Grey-hound to the field?</p>
               <p>Thirdly, is it ſo, that to withhold the ſword from bloud when the Lord calls it forth, procureth the Curſe?<note place="margin">Vſe <hi>3.</hi> Exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</note> then goe thou Text of ours, thou ſhort ſentence of old <hi>Ieremy,</hi> that authentick Prophet: goe (I ſay) into all Brittanne; be as a trumpet to her inhabitants, to ſound an alarme unto war. Thou ſtandeſt upon their ſhelves, lyeſt upon their deskes, art in their houſes, as the other
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18837:22"/> ſentences of the Bible bee: Oh round them in their eare, preſent thy ſelfe to their eyes, that the ſight of thee may make them ſtirre in the Lords quarrell, who have been backward all this while, and make them conſtant that have begunne, untill they have done the worke of the Lord. Thou maieſt be the bolder in thine importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, now the royall head of great Brittanne, our dread Soveraigne, hath taken the courſe to exempt his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes from <hi>this</hi> Curſe, by beginning to draw his wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon for the helpe of the Lord againſt the mighty: and the Lord grant, that like the ſword of <hi>Ionathan,</hi> it may never returne empty. Now, now (I ſay) never lin crying, never lin ſounding in his ſubjects eares, untill Iehovah repaires the ruines of Sion, and ſettle more peace in the Chriſtian world. And inaſmuch, as I have gone thus farre in diſcourſe upon thee, give <hi>mee</hi> leave to give thy Preſſe-money to this worke. And now, O England, where ſhall I begin? whom ſhall I firſt call upon? Might I be ſuffred (and do no wrong to the Text) to ſpeak in an allegory, I would begin with mine owne calling, &amp; wiſh them (as many Champions amongſt them have already done) to dag their pens, dipt in the Fount of holy Writ, as farre into the body of Hereticall Divinity, as <hi>Ehud</hi> did his dagger into <hi>Eglon's bowells,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iudg. 3.20. Ib. ver. 25.</note> that <hi>Errors</hi> ſervants, may <hi>like Eglons, bee aſhamed.</hi> Next, I could entreat the temporall Magiſtrate, to ſtretch forth the ſword of his authority, to the ſpilling of the bloud of thoſe dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous enemies, groſſe impieties, who have got ſuch ſtrength in theſe evill times. Finally, I could adviſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Chriſtian, to uſe a <hi>Metaphoricall</hi> weapon, not <hi>hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie (which woundeth religion under a colour of devotion)</hi> but the ſacrificing knife,<note place="margin">Chryſol. ſerm. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. pag. 28.</note> that ſharp weapon, the ſword of <hi>Repentance,</hi> which may lay ableeding their mightieſt corruptions, that they may never prevaile, nor beare rule againe. But the ſtream of my exhortation muſt not runne in this improper channell. The Text doth not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joine it, though the times doe well require it. I muſt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:18837:22"/> goe more <hi>litterally</hi> to worke, and ſay to this Kingdome, as <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>Ioſhuah, Chuſe out men, and goe out to fight.</hi> Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be he that keepeth not backe his ſword from bloud. Goe out and fight? why? what is there a Moab in the world? and doth Moab provoke us, or provoke God to call us, to draw ſword againſt her? Yes, both.</p>
               <p>Firſt, there is a Romiſh Antichriſt, a Popiſh Faction: and therefore a Moab in the world. For the Romiſh beaſt which now rageth,<note place="margin">How the Pope and his Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are like to Moab. <hi>1.</hi> In their ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginalls.</note> in many particulars may bee compared with that wicked Moab, ſo oft mentioned in the old Teſtament.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Moab was a childe of Inceſt, begat by <hi>Lot</hi> in his drunken fit, of one of his daughters. So Antichriſt is an inceſtuous brat, bred of<note n="*" place="margin">Religio pepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit divitias.</note> 
                  <hi>Religion</hi> the Mother, and of <hi>Riches</hi> the Childe. The Chriſtian <hi>Emperors</hi> in the firſt age after Chriſt, endowed the Church with great reven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues, beſtowed upon Relgion much ſubſtance. Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Biſhops grew drunke with riches; intoxicated with honours: in this their drunken fit committed filthineſſe with worldly wealth, and begate that monſter, the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Whore.</p>
               <p>Secondly, was Moab an <hi>Idolater?</hi> had he his Idoll, and abomination, <hi>Chemoſh?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. King. 12.33.</note> Who groſſer Idolaters than Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts be, who have a multitude of Idolls, and abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions?</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the Moabites were not onely Idolaters themſelves, but alſo enticers of others to Idolatry, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Iſraelites to the ſacrifices of their gods,<note place="margin">Num. 25.2.</note> and drawing <hi>Salomon</hi> himſelfe, notwithſtanding his wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to build an high place for their Idoll Chemoſh.<note place="margin">1. King. 11.7.</note> Doth not the Romiſh Moab draw the whole world to wonder after him; poyſoning the Princes of the earth with his Idolatries, and perverting them, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their wiſedome? Who knowes not how bold his Factors have beene to entice our Goſpellers to their Maſſes &amp; ſuperſtitious ſervices? How many Gentlemen have <hi>their</hi> filthy Cages, <hi>their</hi> Popiſh houſes beyond the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:18837:23"/> Seas, robbed of their ſonnes, deprived of their daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 15.17.</note>Fourthly, Moab got aboundance by wrong. Antichriſt hath rayſed himſelfe to his rule and riches, which is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable, by ſecret villany and open violence.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Iudg 11.17.</note>Fiftly, Moab would not let Iſrael paſſe thorow his land to their place: no more will Antichriſt permit Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, by a free uſe of their conſcience, to paſſe thorow his countryes quietly, to the kingdome of heaven. They of our ſide that have to doe there, unleſſe they bee very wary, are in daily danger of the bloudy Inquiſition. They that dye there, when they lye on their death-beds, are moleſted by the Prieſts with proffers of fopperies and fooleries unto them.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, did the King of Moab ſend <hi>Balaam</hi> on his Aſſe to curſe Iſrael? ſo the Romiſh King of the Romiſh Moab ſends abroad his Bulls,<note place="margin">Num. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Balaams</hi> and Aſſes to curſe and condemne Gods people.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, (for I omit many things) it was propheſied in the old Teſtament, that Moab ſhould be ſmitten with the ſtarre of <hi>Iacob.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Num. 24.17.</note> It is likewiſe propheſied in the new<note n="*" place="margin">2. Theſ. 2.7.</note> Teſtament, that the man of ſinne ſhall bee conſumed <hi>by the breath of the Lords mouth, and with the brightneſſe of his comming.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is a Moab then in the world, O England, a fit <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> for thy ſword, a meete <hi>foe</hi> to fight withall.</p>
               <p>Yea, but what <hi>cauſe</hi> hath England to take ſword a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Moab? what <hi>injurie,</hi> what <hi>wrong</hi> have the <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi> done her?</p>
               <p>What cauſes? No<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> The ſame ſins as cauſes of deſtruction by the ſword, in the Romane Papacy now, that were in Moab in <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies</hi> time. <hi>1.</hi> The pride of Papiſts. <hi>2. Theſ. 2.4.</hi>
                  </note> leſſe than the <hi>Chaldaeans</hi> had to make <hi>their</hi> ſword red with Moabs bloud.</p>
               <p>Firſt, have we not heard of the <hi>pride</hi> of Rome? how that man of ſinne ſitteth in the Temple of God, exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting himſelfe above all that is called God? Have not we heard of a Sunne and a Moone? of a <hi>Vniverſall</hi> Vicar of Chriſt, and a <hi>Catholike</hi> King? of pompous Cardinalls, haughty Biſhops, and proud Prelates?</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:18837:23"/>
               <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Their inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence against God.</note> doth not Romiſh Moab magnifie himſelfe againſt the Lord; adding to his Word, and taking from it what he pleaſeth? How ſawcily doth hee make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the <hi>Lords</hi> Competitor in <hi>title,</hi> in <hi>ſupremacy,</hi> in <hi>autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity,</hi> to deviſe Lawes, and coine Articles of Faith, to make a Purgatory, <hi>Limbus Patrum,</hi> and <hi>Limbus Infan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> to Gods Heaven and Hell? giving his Prieſts pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er (as hee preſumeth) to make a <hi>man,</hi> a <hi>god-man,</hi> fleſh bloud, and bones of a peece of bread; trampling Gods ſtatutes under his feet, to ſet up his owne blaſphemous inventions? and is not England wronged egregiouſly, while the God of England is thus diſhonoured?</p>
               <p>Thirdly, who have ever more injuriouſly oppoſed,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>3</hi> Inſulting over the Church.</note> more imperiouſly inſulted over the Church, than Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts have? Do not they laugh in their ſleeves that they have gulled us with ſugred words, and faire pretences? Doe they not rejoyce in the ruines of the Palatinate of Rhine? and are glad to ſee the Sunne of another <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beths</hi> glory in the eclipſe? How hath the Romiſh Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour inſulted over the perſon of noble Palatine,<note place="margin">Cancel. Hiſp. pag. 65.</note> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling him in baſe and contumelious termes, a <hi>ſlave</hi> or <hi>vaſſaile,</hi> and that to the face of the Engliſh Embaſſador? They that have read the booke of Martyrs, have often ſeen how thoſe Romiſh wolves did crow over the lambes of Chriſt, when once they had gotten them in their pawes. In <hi>deriding Iſrael,</hi> and <hi>reproaching Sion,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Moab came never neer them.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, theſe Romiſh Moabites are a tumultuous broode, confederate in Faction againſt the Church and Religion. The croaking Frogs of this Fen, the Prieſts and Ieſuites, call the Princes of the earth to battell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Saints.<note place="margin">Iudg. 3.12.13</note> Moab once gathered Ammon and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maleck to fight againſt Iſrael, ſo doth the Pope his Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Vaſſailes at this day. What a tumultuous com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact was there betwixt them, in buying and ſelling the Palſgraves poſſeſſions? Cardinall <hi>Lodowick</hi> is the cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall man in that buſineſſe: he ſets downe this poſition,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:18837:24"/> 
                  <hi>That it is more just and profitable,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cancel. Hiſp. pag. 79. 81.</note> 
                  <hi>that ſome Catholicke Prince poſſeſſe the Palatinate, than that Count Fredericke (a Calviniſt, an emulous Prince of the Imperiall dignity, and a perpetuall enemy to the houſe of Auſtria) be reſtored.</hi> Vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this poſition,<note place="margin">Cancel. Hiſp. pag. 90. Ibid. p. 97 98.</note> Biſhop <hi>Caraffa,</hi> the Popes Legate at <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enna</hi> concludes upon <hi>Bavaria</hi> to be the fitteſt man. The <hi>Emperour</hi> next, reſolves upon it, he ſhall be the man: and this reſolution forſooth, hee cannot alter, without the offence of Almighty God. Having ſet downe this reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution with himſelfe, he diſpatcheth a Capuchine Frier, called <hi>Hyacinthus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ibid. p. 96. Ibid. p. 116.</note> to negotiate the buſineſſe with the King of Spaine, becauſe the determination of that tranſlation depended upon Spaine. To worke therefore the Spaniſh King the better to his will, the Popes Legate with the Emperour,<note place="margin">Ib. 108 111.</note> by letter after letter, ſollicites the <hi>Capuchine</hi> to ſlacke no diligence in the buſineſſe. In the meane time,<note place="margin">Ib. 96 98. 101.</note> the Emperour writes to <hi>Don Balthazar Zu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niga,</hi> Councellor of State in the Spaniſh Court. Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>Lodowick</hi> importuneth the Popes Legate at Bruxells,<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> to worke the <hi>Infanta</hi> to this Faction alſo. Now leſt the King of great Brittanne by his Legate, (the Earle of Briſtow, mediating with Spaine about the reſtitution of the Palatinate to his ſonne againe) ſhould hinder the proceedings,<note place="margin">Ibid. p. 106.</note> the Pope forſooth, muſt deviſe a way to ſatisfie him, after the Palatinate ſhould be ſettled upon Bavaria.<note place="margin">Ibid. p. 117</note> Well, the concluſion is, Spaine conjoines in this curſed confederacy, and concludes the buſineſſe in foure Articles.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>That Bavaria ſhall reſtore the upper Auſtria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>That Bavaria ſhall content himſelfe with the Electorall voice, and upper Palatinate onely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>That Spaine ſhould have the lower Palatinate, and Bavaria diſclaime all title thereto.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>That the Emperour and Spaniſh King ſhall make a league together, to make an offenſive and defenſive warre againſt whomſoever ſhould reſiſt their proceedings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Were not here Moabs <hi>tumultuous ones?</hi> Was not here
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:18837:24"/> 
                  <hi>Geball,</hi> and <hi>Ammon,</hi> and <hi>Amalak, Philiſtia</hi> and thoſe of <hi>Tyre,</hi> joyned together againſt Gods Iſrael?</p>
               <p>In which confederacy, how <hi>falſly</hi> they dealt under faire pretences, appeares by <hi>this,</hi> that while <hi>Spaine</hi> ſpoiled the <hi>daughter</hi> of her dominions, he glozed with the <hi>father,</hi> and pretended a marriage with the brother. And while the <hi>Emperour</hi> promiſed our King to ſtay the execution of the proſcription againſt the <hi>Palatinate,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cancel. Hiſp. p. 67. Ibid. 75. Ibid. 77. Ibid 78.</note> 
                  <hi>Bavaria</hi> procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the ſame, and the Emperour thanked him for it, encouraged him in it. The doctrine of equivocation is ſo well ſtudied of theſe Romiſh Moabites, that in moſt of their waightieſt affayres with Proteſtant Princes, <hi>lyes</hi> and <hi>falſehoods</hi> ſtrike the greateſt ſtroke: pretences of u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and practiſes of enmity, are found no where more than amongſt them.</p>
               <p>Theſe things conſidered, never had Chaldaea greater cauſe to fight with Moab, than wee with Rome:<note place="margin">Vti olim de Philippo Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonico dixit Demoſtheues Athenienſibus. <hi>orat. Olynt. 1.</hi>
                  </note> and <hi>if ever with her,</hi> then <hi>now,</hi> while the bloud of the Saints ſhed by her, doe call for vengeance; and while the ſnares which ſhe layeth for the bloud royall of the Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh race, beſides other manifeſt wrongs, doe call us Brittaines to goe forth againſt her. <hi>Now,</hi> a neceſſity to this worke lyeth upon us. Fit <hi>purſes</hi> for <hi>contribution</hi> muſt now ſtand open, fit <hi>perſons</hi> for <hi>execution</hi> are now called upon: neyther (as I conceive) can any good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon bee given, why eyther of both ſhould now bee ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. Gird your ſwords therefore upon your thighes, O you valiant ones, and ride on with courage and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowne. Our <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> ſummons againſt this Moab: what ranke, what degree amongſt the <hi>Gentry,</hi> amongſt the <hi>Commonalty</hi> of his dominions, may not account it their glory, to have an hand in this enterpriſe?</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Gentry,</hi> the golden bubble upon the breſt,<note place="margin">Vid. Alexand. ab Alexand. l. 5. c. 16. &amp; Draud. in Sched Reg. pag. 315. 316.</note> little moones upon the ſhoes, gold rings upon the hands, gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den chaines about the necke, garments of purple given by Princes (the ancient Enſignes of nobility) were but ioyes to grace nobility with, in compariſon to heroicke
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:18837:25"/> exploites in <hi>Gods</hi> cauſe, for the Church her right. Oh that Gentlemen, fit for this ſervice, would delight more to weare their <hi>armes</hi> in field, than to paint them in their houſes, grave them in their ſeales, place them in their portalls, and weave them in their Sumpter-cloathes. Then, to be ſure, their holding of Armes would not bee ſo much for worldlings to behold them, as for the Church to be beholding to them for the ſame.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Commonalty.</hi> If the <hi>generous</hi> ſort muſt take ſword againſt Moab, and it be their glory ſo to do; then let not the <hi>meaner</hi> and <hi>vulgar</hi> ſort think it any diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to goe forth under them. When Preſſes come, if their places and charge will permit it, (as Officers that preſſe, ought to have a ſpeciall regard to that, and to doe nothing for ſiniſter reſpects) let not them frame worthleſſe pretences to ſhift their Princes call. If they hide their heads, when they ſhould encourage their owne hearts in Gods cauſe that calls on them; if they chuſe rather (as the manner of ſome is) to ſtarve in woodes, than to ſtirre to warres, or coine lies and falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoodes to delude the Officers: I doe not ſee how they can eſcape the Curſe which the Text <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oth ſpeake of, and bring a bleſſing upon their heads. Be bold there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the Lord, and be ſtrong in the power of his might: you could never ſtirre in a more needefull time; your ſword <hi>now</hi> may doe more acceptable ſervice for the Lord, than it could have done for many yeeres. When Moab is curbed,<note place="margin">Iudg. 3.30. Iſa. 16. ult. chap. 25.10.</note> Iſrael ſhall have reſt; when Moabs glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is abated, and troden downe as ſtraw for the dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hill, then diſtreſſed Sion ſhall have glory, and her ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſtones in our neighbour-nations ſhall bee gathered together againe. If you ſay, we could be content to bee forward, were we ſure of ſucceſſe: I anſwer, doubt not of that,<note place="margin">Ioſ. 7. Iudg. 5.15.</note> if <hi>Chemeſh,</hi> if <hi>Achan,</hi> if the diviſions of <hi>Ruben,</hi> if ſecret well-wiſhers to the Romiſh cauſe, and ſlightnes in ſeeking to the God of all Armies, doe not croſſe us. Let the <hi>abomination</hi> of <hi>Moab</hi> bee kept under amongſt us
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:18837:25"/> at home, and the mighty of Moab ſhall not conquer us abroad. Let ſuch men as hide the Babyloniſh garment in the rotten tents of their Popiſh hearts, who (having a face for the Prince, and an heart for the Pope) would be glad of an opportunity to betray their country for a wedge of gold, have nothing to doe in our Campes. Let not the Nobles of <hi>Iudah</hi> ſend letters to <hi>Tobiah,</hi> nor reveale the matters of <hi>Nehemiah</hi> to him.<note place="margin">Neh. 6.17, 19.</note> Let Popiſh Ladies have no acquaintance with State-ſecrets, (for then <hi>Balaam</hi> and <hi>Balak</hi> ſhall bee ſure to know them:) Let the loyall ſubjects with an unanimous conſent, adde ſinewes to the warre, and let not corrupt Officers make thoſe ſinewes to ſhrinke. In a word, let the Lord bee ſought carefully in all our proceedings, and then the <hi>God of Iacob</hi> will be with us, the <hi>Lord of Hosts</hi> will fight for us, and proſper our handy-worke.<note place="margin">Bern. ad Milit. Templ. c. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Securi igitur pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedite milites, &amp; intrepido animo inimicos crucis Christi pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellite.</hi> In the bowels of Chriſt Ieſus put forth your hands to the worke of the Lord: let not your ſpirits fayle in your bodies, let not your ſwords ruſt in their ſheaths, let not your coyne fret in your cheſts. And you that can do nothing this way, with your <hi>purſes</hi> or with your <hi>perſons,</hi> fight with your prayers to the God of heaven; bee mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and evening in his preſence Chamber with your ſuites: tell him, that for Sions ſake you <hi>cannot</hi> bee ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, nor yet <hi>will</hi> be, untill hee hath made bare his arme in his owne cauſe, cloathed his foes with the robes of ſhame, and compaſſed his Saints with ſongs of delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
